<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hard way to heaven explained and applyed in a sermon intended to be preached at Peters-Cornhill, but by reason of the disorderly concourse preached at St. Katherines Creed-Church London, the 27th of July 1662, being the third day after his release / by Z. Crofton.</title>
            <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29659</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11191152</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11191152</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35044)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1439:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hard way to heaven explained and applyed in a sermon intended to be preached at Peters-Cornhill, but by reason of the disorderly concourse preached at St. Katherines Creed-Church London, the 27th of July 1662, being the third day after his release / by Z. Crofton.</title>
                  <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Taken as (preached) in characters compared with his own notes providentially lost and brought to our hands. Now published to check and correct the misrepresentations thereof by the sons of slander and subjects of weakness."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew VII, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46624:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Hard way to HEAVEN: Explained and applyed in A SERMON Intended to be preached at <hi>Peters-Cornhill:</hi> but by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the diſorderly Concourſe preached at St. <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines Creed-Church London:</hi> the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> 1662. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the third day after his releaſe.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Z. CROFTON</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Buttolphs-Algate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Taken as (Preached) in Characters compared with his own Notes providentially loſt and brought to our hands. Now publiſhed to check and correct the miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof by the Sons of ſlander and Subjects of weakneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46624:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46624:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe untrue and direct contrary reports of this Sermon, and its Authour, extort the publication thereof. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> will not do it, he contenteth himſelf in the conſcience of his integrity, and accounts it <hi>an eaſie thing to be judged of men;</hi> yea of good men; his good name is the Churches advantage, and ought to be preſerved and defended againſt the calumnies of the wicked, and cenſures of the weak, who wound not him without, more deeply wounding their own ſouls.</p>
            <p>I having written this Sermon from his mouth in ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and (by his Notes loſt by his Son, and by Providence di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to my hand) having ſupplyed what time and the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the audience cauſed him to pretermit: I thought it my duty to hazard the diſcontent of my friend and Paſtour, and to preſent thee with the ſame, that by unprejudiced <hi>reading</hi> thou mayeſt be undeceived, edified, and enabled to contradict the clamours of the ſons of ſlander, and check the cenſure of the over-credulous ſubjects of weakneſs, though not of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Recantation is moſt ſtrangely expected from him who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet was charged, or by argumentation was convinced of an errour, on whom no terms or conditions for obtainment of Liberty was once impoſed, or ſo much as propoſed by any perſon whatſover, whoſe non-conformity was fully, freely, and (to the honour of the honourable Perſons before whom he was convened) acceptably declared, and the occaſion, yea forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of which is no other then a conſciencious practice, and profeſſion of principles he ever ſtated in his late conteſts for Reformation.</p>
            <p>I wonder to finde ſome ſerious Chriſtians ſcandalized at Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s attendance on Gods ſolemn publick worſhip, celebrated according to the order of the Common Prayer Book, and to hear men cenſure him for the ſame, as if defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb facs="tcp:46624:3"/> and an apoſtate from the cauſe of Reformation; in which he appeared with ſo much vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our; I muſt tell the Reader, ſuch as ſate under his miniſtry cannot but know and witneſs he ever adjudged againſt <hi>ſeparation</hi> in his moſt earneſt perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or endeavours for reformation, he alway diſſwaded <hi>non-communion of members,</hi> as <hi>non-conformity of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> and did conſtantly and convincingly affirm, that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial diſorder and corrupt appendents in Gods worſhip was not a ſufficient cauſe of perſonal abſence or non-attendents on the ſame, he ever concluded guilt on the Church Collective by theſe diſorders and corruptions, which did not ſtain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals looking to their own perſonal actings in their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary attendance on Gods Ordinance: Verily we muſt ſay Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> in priſon did only practice what he preached whilſt at liberty.</p>
            <p>Such was Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> care and condition in his late con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts for reformation, not to be eſteemed an Advocate for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, or an approver of non-communion (much leſſe a Martyr for them) that in his late writing he profeſſeth his judgement and reſolution againſt them.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>Analepſis, or St. Peters bonds abiding,</hi> thou haſt him thus profeſſing, I proteſt whatſoever ſhall be the eſtabliſhment in the Church, though never ſo corrupt, whilſt conſiſtent with ſalvation, though it may occaſion to me ſufferings, and the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of my miniſtry; by Gods grace it ſhall not effect in me, or ſuch on whom I have influence, Schiſme from the Church.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>Analepſis Anaelephthe, or the faſtning of St. Peters bonds,</hi> he avoweth, this reformation cannot juſtifie the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, for that the corruptions eſtabliſhed were never made ſuch eſſential parts of worſhip, as to make a ſufficient ground for ſeparation. The ſober, zealous Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, who groaned under the burden of theſe corruptions, and for this reformation, were grieved by, and greatly contended againſt the ſeparation, as that which was without
<pb facs="tcp:46624:3"/> ſufficient ground, yea like Jeſus Chriſt their Maſter, they kept communion with a Church, whoſe doctrine and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was in much need of reformation, yea, and they taught men ſo to do.</p>
            <p>And in his Epiſtle to Mr. <hi>Firmius Liturgical Conſiderator Conſidered,</hi> in which he apologiſeth for Miniſters not read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (not for members not learning) the Common Prayer Book; he tells us expreſly his judgement and reſolution in theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words. I am ſo much affected to the peace of the Church that I have of late preached what God aſsiſting, I reſolve to practiſe: <hi>viz.</hi> many and great corruptions in Gods worſhip are to be grieved for patiently, and groaned under, before Schiſmes be conſented unto, and ſeparation conſulted, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided nevertheleſs, I be paſsive not active: I can keep com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion under that form of worſhip, whereby I cannot admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and heartily ſay Amen to the matter of thoſe Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans which are put up in an order ſo confuſed, prepoſterous, and indigeſted, that it ſeemeth to me to be ſo much below the gravity of the Church, whoſe mouth I muſt be, the ſeriouſneſs of the office whereby I miniſter, the ſanctity of the duty I am to perform, and the ſacred nature of the object to whom they are preſented, that I dare not ſtand between God and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Let theſe paſſages and the like in his late writings be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as the beſt of his Judgement and Conſcience, and let malice it ſelf read in his practiſe the leaſt contradiction to his Cauſe or Principles, or defection from the ſame, or not read with half an eye an exact conformity to himſelf, and clear obedience to his judgement, in a non-conforming communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Good Reader be pleaſed to obſerve, that Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s attendance on the ſolemn worſhip of God in the Tower, and in the Common Prayer Book order, is ſo far from being the reſult of his reſtraint, and effect of temptation, or any condition in order to his releaſe, that his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ever for it: He never did conceive that Order
<pb facs="tcp:46624:4"/> (though to be corrected) a moral ſufficient bar to this duty; and therefore the very firſt day he came in priſoner, he did deſire of the Lieutenant the liberty of going to Church, and not obtaining it, he did demand it the next day from his Gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; he did many times petition for the ſame, and ſollicited the obtainment thereof many months before he did obtain it: nay I muſt further acquaint thee; it is now neer upon a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat year ſince Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> it being rumored that he went to the Church in the Tower, and he heard Common Prayer, did write a full Apology and defence of his practice (which was then but in the view) in that caſe; this Apology paſſed through my hands to many good people and Miniſters, who would not undertake to convince the ſame of error, though they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſcandalize him and his practice, and hindered the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I note unto thee Reader, that thou mayeſt ſee Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s practice in this caſe is not new or raſh, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved and deliberate, and is ſo far from defection from, that it is an upright walking according to his apprehenſions of the Goſpel. Howſoever I could, I will not now dilate in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his principles and practice, nor break out to a large and ſharp invective againſt the licentiouſneſs of the tongues, and the lying ſpirits of ſeeming Saints ſo notoriouſly extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant againſt a perſon ſo innocent and upright, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expoſed to the violence and rage of men on both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams of Reformation; for hereby I know I ſhould incenſe him, whoſe diſpleaſure will be great for doing this, which I could not in peace have left undone.</p>
            <p>Let me aſſure thee, Mr. <hi>Crofton's</hi> judgement is in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticks the very ſame it was before his confinement; he then could not now cannot conform; he then could, now can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, and give an <hi>Amen</hi> to the matter of Prayers, whoſe order his judgement muſt and doth condemn: He was then, is now zealous for reformation, and againſt ſeparation: He then reſolved, and now reſolveth, to ſeek Church purity by union with the Church, and to abide in the houſe; he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth to cleanſe, to bring his offerings unto the Lord, when
<pb facs="tcp:46624:4"/> that his ſoul doth loath them by reaſon of the prophane hands and prepoſterous order, in which the ſons of <hi>Eli</hi> do preſent them.</p>
            <p>I know it to be his burden to obſerve the baſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd brood of non-communicating ſeparating Sects, taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vagrants, and whipt home to their reputed parents, to lie at the door and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rk under the wings of reforming non-Conformi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, who did ever diſown them, and drive them out as not theirs, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to their honeſt deſign. I know Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> to be zealous leaſt the policy of ſome, and weakneſs of others ſhould ſo far embrace thoſe, as to make ſpectators think them their natural Children. I know Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is ſenſible many are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to him in negatives, againſt prophaneſs, againſt ſuperſtition, againſt corruption, againſt diſorder; but are his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in poſitives for no order, for no communion, for no Church. I am ſure Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath ſadly reſented that ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal under which Non-conformity groans, and is made odious, <hi>viz.</hi> It is a ſpirit of contradiction againſt every thing, but for nothing. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> well knoweth thoſe who clamour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his communion, make Church entity, not Church purity, their quarrell and controverſie: He hath obſerved their Church gathering commenced and proceeded under the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of Reformation, and unto the ſupplanting and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion thereof. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is convinced, that Chriſts true Church, though corrupt, and Chriſts own Ordinances, though diſorderly adminiſtred, are to be embraced, adheared unto, and attended, when the flocks of Chriſts companions are to be avoided. I am confident Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is reſolved to follow his Lord when come from the flock to thethreſhold of the Temple, but he dareth not go before him. Reader, if this be an error, help Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> to conviction, and then thou mayeſt hear his recantation; in the mean time joyn with me in prayer, that God will give repentance to the men who have called good evil, and evil good, and uncharitably repreſented a conſciencious practice, of well conſidered, openly declared, deliberately reſolved principles, to be an apoſtacie, defection,
<pb facs="tcp:46624:5"/> recantation, back-ſliding, baſe complying, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
            <p>The Lord encreaſe the number of ſuch Apoſtates, who will by preaching, writing, and practiſe, under the reproach and rage of all men, ſhew their endeavours of reformation, in that ſtrait gate and narrow way of careful, induſtrious, non-conforming communion with the Church in Chriſts Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, between thoſe rocks which on each hand work its ruine: This is the hearty deſire and prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt 9. 1662.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thine in and for the ſimplicity of the Goſpel. H. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46624:5"/>
            <head>THE Hard way to Heaven. EXPLAINED &amp; APPLYED. <hi>In a Sermon Preached on the</hi> 27 <hi>of</hi> July 1662.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>The Text</hi> Matthew <hi>7.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Becauſe ſtraite is the Gate, and narrow is the Way, which leadeth unto life.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Cannot but conceive many in this audience (acted more by curioſity then Chriſtianity) come with an expectation, that I will declare and diſcourſe the things of my ſelf, or Gods dealings with me in my late condition: But I muſt let you know, I muſt herein diſappoint you; Experiencies of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is my own Comfort, what was to me in common with other Chriſtians, I ſhall declare to your edification; and that is in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, <hi>the ſerious reflections of my thoughts under the Strates of my late condition,</hi> concerning which I may ſay as that eminent Martyr of our reformed Religion, <hi>John Philpot,</hi> ſaid in the like caſe, <hi>in the Lollards Tower paſſing through ſix or ſeaven doors, I came to my Logdeing thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugh many Straits,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to remembrance, <hi>Strait is the Gate and narrow is the way which leadeth unto Life;</hi> The ſtrait paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which lead to glory, ought to be alwayes pondered, but the thoughts thereof are moſt proper, and profitable when we are locked up in them, and the ſence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by a neceſſity of ſuffering what we cannot eſcape without ſin, the Heathen accounted it their honour to repreſent virtue to be a <hi>Strait and narrow way,</hi> and therefore it ſelf the reward of all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in and for it, ſure I am; it is the Glory of Chriſtianity, that it was never Propounded to the world as an eſtate of eaſe: Chriſt was never Preached without his Croſs, nor was Heavens
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46624:6"/> Glory ever declared without a determination of hardſhip in the attainment thereof: <hi>Strait i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Gate, and narrow is the way which leadeth unto life;</hi> is the Doctrine Preached by the Lord himſelfe, and the truth thereof is dayly proved by the experience of his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Theſe words are part of our Saviours Sermon preached in the Mountain, in which many particular Doctrines and ſpecial du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, were by him Stated, and directed: whether this Sermon was a ſet Solemn and Continued diſcourſe, of the Preacher (as by its Circumſtance it ſeemeth to have been, or the Evangiliſts Collection, and compoſure of thoſe many paſſages, and particular diſcourſes which paſſed from our Saviour on ſeverall occaſions, at ſundry times (as <hi>Calvin</hi> doth conceive) I ſhall not now ſtand to enquire or debate.</p>
            <p>In the foregoing verſe our Saviour perſwadeth his hearers to an hard Task <hi>Enter in at the Strait gate:</hi> and enforceth his exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with, and by a diſparity of the different paths in which men paſſe unto different ends. <hi>For wide is the Gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be who go in thereat: becauſe ſtrait is the Gate, and narrow is the way which leadeth unto life, and few there be who find it;</hi> the one is <hi>eaſie</hi> and <hi>undoing,</hi> the other is <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note>Our Text is the ſecond and Counter part of our Saviours rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that way which is hard in its paſſage, but happy in its end, And it is in its ſelf an entire propoſition, and ſo ſhall ſtand for our point of Doctrine, which we ſhall proſecute by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and application. <hi>Strait is the Gate, and narrow is the way to life.</hi> Firſt by way of Explication.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</note>
               <hi>I</hi> will not ſpend time in noting to you the many Readings and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſions of this propoſition, only obſerve the ancient Copies to read the ſame as a propoſition of admiration. <hi>How ſtrait is the Gate! How narrow is the way which leadeth unto life!</hi> but this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Emphaſis in no hindrance of its agrumentation it giveth no cauſe of controverſſie.</p>
            <p>This propoſition falleth into two parts to be particularly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subject or thing ſpoken of <hi>The gate and way to life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">The Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</note>2. The predicate, or thing ſpoken of it; <hi>It is ſtrait and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe in order, and firſt of the Subject, or thing ſpoken of,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46624:6"/> and therein we have two things alſo obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The End, Life;<note place="margin">The end of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, ſtrife</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The means under this Metaphor a <hi>Gate,</hi> a <hi>way, life is</hi> that end, and eſtate which is to be aimed at, and driven unto by the <hi>Gate and way,</hi> which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt doth advice and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, this is the marke all muſt ſtrive to hit, the prize of our high Calling; All muſt preſs to poſſeſſe; for this, leſt by ſhooting ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t or wide, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th utterly undo us, and ſinck us in perdition: <hi>I</hi> ſay it is <hi>Life</hi> an undoubted Bleſſings, a moſt eminent Bleſſing,<note place="margin">Iob. 26 4</note> the Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, the Entity of all bleſſings, peace, plenty, honour, and dignity are meer nullaties to dead men, a Worm is as much as a Crown to a man in the grave; he who is not, cannot be rich or honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; whatever be mans eſtate, he is only happy by <hi>being;</hi> take away his life,<note place="margin">Prov 3.16.8.35.</note> and you take hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all <hi>life</hi> is the chief of bleſſings to be purſued with utmoſt Diligence preſerved with ut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moſt Care, and purchaſed at the deareſt rate, <hi>All that a man hath he will give for his life:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life.</note> The Devil well knew the worth of this Jewel, when he durſt preſume to put at <hi>Job</hi> to pawn his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; Integrity: the inſenſible eternity of his life, to the ſecuring of a preſent tranſient puff thereof. But the life in my Text is more than a bare naked life, it is the <hi>life</hi> which is in the right hand of wiſdom, which comprehendeth all goodneſs, real good; this is not a <hi>natural life,</hi> though that is to be preſerved and prized; yet for the ſecuring of this life, it is to be parted from and loſt; of,<note place="margin">Math. 16.25.</note> &amp; in this ſenſe, our Saviour hath determined <hi>he who will ſave his life muſt looſe it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life.</note> The natural life capacitateth to the enjoyment of the good things of God, but this life gives us the enjoyment of our good God himſelfe: this life is not the <hi>ſpiritual life;</hi> I do not mean in reſpect of its <hi>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure and quality,</hi> for ſo it is ſpiritual; but I mean, it is not ſuch in reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect of degree, and ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the life of Grace (the ſame in kind) is diſtinguiſhed, as dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the life of Glory:<note place="margin">but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</note> this life giveth us a Converſe with God remote, and at a diſtance ſubject to weakneſs and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and many heat chilling, almoſt heart killing interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and cloudy diſpenſations: But the life in our Text gives us the enjoyment of God immediately <hi>in his preſence:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.12.</note> fully in <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:</hi> perfectly ſeeing him and knowing him, as ſeen and known of him, and <hi>eternal y</hi> without parting from him, or his parting from us, this is the River of Life which runneth in the City of God: into Rivers of pleaſure in his preſence for evermore:<note place="margin">Rev. 1.22.</note> it is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46624:7"/> therefore that which Chriſtians in Scripture-language call the <hi>life of God, the life of Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>life of Glory, life everlaſting.</hi> It abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth after the natural life is expired, it aboundeth beyond what the ſpiritual life (as diſtinct from this life) doth or can extend unto. This life is the Emphaſis, the excellency of <hi>Eternity</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof the ſubject Eternity ſimply and in the abſtract, is an amazing dismaying property, a ſoul that ſitteth, or walketh in the vale of the ſhadow of death, and caſteth his eye on the black, boundleſs, bottomleſs Ocean of Eternity, findeth the ſame to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect, affrighting dreadful apprehenſions on his ſoul; which are appeaſed and made comfortable by onely diſcerning <hi>eternity</hi> is the adjunct unto nature: Men cannot without dread and terror ſhoot the Gulph of natural death, becauſe thereby they paſs into eternity, it is the aſſurance of life in eternity, which encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſoul in ſo ſad paſſage, and this life eternal is the City, end, eſtate, unto which the Gate and way in our Text doth lead.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The means to life.</note>The means conducing to this end is by a Metaphor called and compared to a Gate, to a way, and as ſuch it doth repreſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſerious obſervation, the <hi>nature,</hi> the <hi>order,</hi> and the <hi>number</hi> of that means which doth effect, or by which men muſt work out their own Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Its nature.</note>Firſt, this Metaphor doth note unto us the <hi>nature of the means of Grace,</hi> which tends unto Glory: It is a <hi>Gate; and a way:</hi> a Gate a way, are places of perſonal motions under ſpecial preſcription, and limitation unto ſome peculiar place or end: and theſe places are denominated Gates and Ways in relation to their terminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the neceſſity of mens motion in them: a Gate: as that cloſe paſſage, by which if men do not enter, they can no way move in the <hi>Way,</hi> or <hi>Street</hi> which leadeth further. The way is that narrow bounded paſſage, by, or in which men can onely move in ſafety, unto the place at which they would arive, if they ſtep out of theſe bounds they are treſpaſſers and in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and therefore by their perſonal motion, under theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions,<note place="margin">Prov. 3.19.4.11. Pſal. 118.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> they can only arrive at their deſired places: this then doth teach us. The means which muſt effect eternal life, <hi>is mans perſonal motion, and activity under Gods preſcriptions, directions, and limitations;</hi> theſe are the paths <hi>of peace,</hi> the way <hi>of wiſdom,</hi> and the Gates <hi>of righteouſneſs,</hi> the termination muſt be from God, but the motion muſt be from man, the Lord doth ſet, but man muſt keep within theſe bounds, direction is divine obſervation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46624:7"/> muſt be humane; euery man who will get Heaven,<note place="margin">Gen. 17. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 1.10.</note> muſt go to Heaven in Gods way: he who will win God, muſt walke with God, according to the will of God. <hi>He that will wear the Crown of righteouſneſs muſt ran the race of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12 1.</note> eternal life cannot be obtained by humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor without humane motion, or induſtry, they will equally miſcarry, who ſtand ſtill in, or ſtrike out of the way, which God directeth, and hath determined: <hi>Iſrael could never have poſſeſſed</hi> Laiſh <hi>though the Gates ſtood open, if they had ſtood ſtill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 18.</note> 
               <hi>and not advanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards it.</hi> Heaven is not the event of idleneſs, but of activity: when the Lord hath once bounded, determined, directed the Gate: the way of life muſt move in it with all care and conſtancy,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 9.12. Luke 13.24. 1 Cor. 9.24. Phil. 3.14.2.12.</note> diligence, endeavour, induſtry is required from men for the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of their Salvation; They are called upon to <hi>fight, ſtrive,</hi> and <hi>wreſtle, run, preſs, proceed,</hi> in Gods Commandements: to work out their own Salvation: I could never yet underſtand or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the mute, non moving Religion of ſuch <hi>Quakers</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend moſt to Gods Guidance. Miſerable are the deſires and hopes of life, which ſtrive not unto the attainment and ſecurity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; vain are the profeſſions of God, which provoke not motion towards God, ſuch who call Chriſt, <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> hear him, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the truth of what he ſpeaketh, but will not <hi>do what he ſaith,</hi> will find the Gate of life ſhut againſt them when they would but cannot have admittance; not every one who ſaith <hi>Lord, Lord, but he who doth the will of my Father,</hi> are in the Gate, the way,<note place="margin">ver. 21.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> ſaith our Saviour in this very Sermon, and ſhortly after this very Text: God hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined his worſhip, declared his will, appointed his Ordinances, Men therefore muſt with all care, caution, conſtancy and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, attend, obſerve, and do the ſame, the Gate, the way to life is mans <hi>activity</hi> in faith and obedience: mans <hi>labour</hi> in word and Sacraments, Mans <hi>induſtry</hi> to do the ſeveral duties of his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and particular Calling; having known the will of God, we muſt up and be doing, having ſeen the way of righteouſneſs, we muſt ſtretch our Limbs, and actively ſtrive and preſs forward in it: though man is <hi>Paſſive</hi> in receiving the firſt Principles of Grace, and all ſubſequent ſtrength to duty, he muſt be an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in the purſuit of Glory. I never could believe man had of himſelfe <hi>free will to good;</hi> nor that man could ever enjoy God, without doing good, with the force of a <hi>free will:</hi> God may turn our faces towards <hi>Zion,</hi> but we muſt go thither on our own legs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46624:8"/> they <hi>go from ſtrength to ſtrength every one in</hi> Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on <hi>until they appear b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7.</note> Chriſt Ieſus may firſt <hi>apprehend us</hi> but we muſt <hi>follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reach, forth unto thoſe things which are before us,</hi> preſs forward that we may <hi>ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rehend that for which we are apprehended of him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3 12.</note> the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rings may enforce, but the wheels themſelves move in the clock, the Spirit helpeth our infirmitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; But we muſt <hi>pray, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> &amp;c. It is Chriſt who <hi>ſtrengthneth us;</hi> but content in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12.</note> knowled<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e how to want, and abound, patience under provoking afflictions, muſt be our own act: Salvation is God gift, but we muſt ſeek it, and receive it like our ſelves, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, ſtudious, zealous, conſtant motion in the way of God commandements: he tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſits ſtill when he ſees his way, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to his journeys end; the natural language of ſaving conviction, is, <hi>what ſhall we, do.</hi> Be aſſured (Chriſtians) the who <hi>enter</hi> not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate,<note place="margin">Acts. 2 37.</note> 
               <hi>move</hi> not in the way, get not unto life Be ye therefore <hi>not ſlothful but followers of them, who</hi> through fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto duty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.11.12. Its order.</note> and patience) in difficulty <hi>inherit the promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in this Metaphor we may obſerve as the nature, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>order of the means which leadeth unto life:</hi> it is <hi>a Gate,</hi> a <hi>way,</hi> fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Gate,</hi> then a <hi>Way,</hi> mens motion unto entrance, and after pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in the way of Gods preſcription, and limitation: God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God of order; nor muſt we think him more regula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in humane ſociety, the things of the world, then in the Affairs which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern his own Glory, and his peoples Salvation; they who act pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtrouſly in the things which conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n men, do reproach the maker, and they who act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> offerouſly in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which concern God, reproach th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Redeemer, nature a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> neceſſity doth make a <hi>Gate of entrance,</hi> proceed the <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of progreſs.</hi> to any propounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end: <hi>Inch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion</hi> muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> before <hi>proceſs:</hi> thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there is in ſome ſenſe and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e an <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trance</hi> without <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>greſs</hi> in the wayk of God, there cannot po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be a <hi>pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſs</hi> without <hi>entrance</hi> many may indeed <hi>begin in point,</hi> but <hi>end</hi> in the fleſh: run well in the firſt acts, but be hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred in the cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe of Chriſtianity: after they have <hi>known</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way of righteouſneſs, and <hi>eſcaped</hi> the pollutions which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the world through luſt, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay be again <hi>entangled therein, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> overcome and turn fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m the holy Commandement:</hi> ſome who are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> far from the Kingdom of Heaven, may fall ſhort of it: and ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who are <hi>alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt,</hi> may never be <hi>altogether Chriſtians,</hi> but none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> walk in him, who have not firſt <hi>rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ied Chriſt the Lord:</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can be edified, who are not entred into the moſt holy Faith
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46624:8"/> the Scriptures, and Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nances of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.130. Heb. 6.1</note> do repreſent unto us the <hi>Gate</hi> before the <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> of Glory: the entrance of the word of God which doth make wiſe the ſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, <hi>the firſt principles of the Oracles of God,</hi> the <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undations</hi> of ſaith, the firſt <hi>Conception and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ming Chriſt</hi> in the ſoul; the Sacraments of God are ſuited to this order. <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is a ſeal of an <hi>Imitation</hi> to the Church, <hi>engraf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> into Chriſt, <hi>Incorporation</hi> to the Saints: The Lords ſupper is a Sacrament of <hi>growth and continuance</hi> in Chriſt of <hi>progreſs</hi> in the way of ſaith, and true Religion and ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> move not in this order, cannot poſſibly paſs unto eternal life: It is in Grace and Religion, as in nature, and ſecular affairs, and in both: It is all one, not to undertake an enterprize, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o invert the order of motion, neceſſary to any end: They t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at <hi>enter not the Gate,</hi> may <hi>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and go for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard, but <hi>not into t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e City:</hi> they who lay not the foundation, may form a frame, but cannot build any ſtanding ſtructure: ſuch who ſecure not their Birth, and are not rooted in Chriſt, cannot grow up in him: It is with many prepoſterous Chriſtians, as with raſh g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ddy Concellors, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Conqueſt, and divide the Bears skin, before they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the war-fare, or go out to kill the Bear, or like wandring beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, who being in conſtant motion, neither know nor care whither they go, ſo they have but an houſe in their eye: ſo many having heard of Heaven, and Holineſs wander with a blind affection any ways, in which they may keep that within ſight: but never conſider whether they have entred the Gate of this Encloſure: Let me tell you, many will prove this deſtructive to them, that they take a view of the <hi>dignitys,</hi> without any care of the <hi>dutys</hi> of a Chriſtian, and grow great and ſtrong in the <hi>joye, confidence,</hi> and <hi>expectations</hi> of Saints who are ſtrangers, yea ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the principles and practiſes of piety, to the fund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal doctrines of faith, and ordinances of worſhip; I have with amazement obſerved deluded ſouls, to have paſſed from ſome groſs prophaneneſs, Idolatrys, and Superſtitions, and to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in by paths, with the greateſt ſecurity, alacrity, confidence, joy, profeſſing (to the Blaſphemy of the Goſpel, Shame of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and Scandal of Religion) the fulleſt aſſurance of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in, and approach unto eternal life, that is imaginable: and this not onely under the greateſt ſufferings, but alſo the moſt groſſe errors, and grievous ſins, prid perſidie, perjury, ſchiſmes, ſeditions, treaſons, and rebellions, which were even perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46624:9"/> under the Sun;<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4 5</note> and what is more with an heaven daring boldneſſe, affirming their abominations to be the cauſe of God; <hi>I</hi> could never conceive other cauſe thereof then this, they having gotten a ſight of heaven, taſted the good word of God, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the world to come: giddily to run out without any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the <hi>Gate</hi> care of <hi>entrance,</hi> regard unto the <hi>Foundation</hi> knowledge of, <hi>Firſt principals of Religion;</hi> but with a blind affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, move forward in any eſtate? and it is poſſible to move toward it, and not come into it, to keep it in ſight, in a way which lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not into it, they deceive themſelves, defend all their errors and Impieties, and will not hear of a deviation, becauſe <hi>Heaven is in their Eye,</hi> Life is within their view, glory is in their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as if <hi>Balaam</hi> were ſure to dye, the death of the Righteous, when and becauſe he and all his conſpirations, and endeavours to curſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaw their glory and the good will of God unto them: Beloved friends conſider mens Eſtate is <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> or <hi>unconverted,</hi> as to God, Chriſt, and true Religion, the <hi>unconverted</hi> muſt make ſure they <hi>enter</hi> the Gate, the ſtrait Gate learn Principles of faith, lay in their Souls the Foundations of, Religion: the <hi>Converted</hi> muſt with care and caution move in the Narrow way without deviation, or divertion without going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide or going back: If you have not rightly entered talk what you will, <hi>I</hi> cannot but ſuſpect your attainments in grace; many of you talk of Religion, and ſeem to be zealous for it, forward in it whoſe confuſed notions, deluded apprehenſions, and deviating Converſations, do witneſſe you have not <hi>entered the Gate,</hi> or at leaſt, and beſt are <hi>gone aſide from the way that leadeth to life:</hi> Look to Gods order,<note place="margin">Iob. 18.4.</note> if ever you will live with God in honour, whatever Religions humour may act you to invite Gods order, you muſt know the Earth muſt not be removed for you; if you will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly minde Gods method, you muſt and will miſcarry in your deſignes,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.2.20 21, 22, 23.</note> and intentions for his life and glory, for ſad is their eſtate who profeſſe to perſue, and yet never enter the pathes of peace, and more ſad is theirs who entered into the way of Righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, <hi>turne aſide</hi> from the holy Comandements.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the means.</note>The third thing which lieth in this Metaphor is the <hi>number of the means of Grace.</hi> It is a <hi>Gate</hi> a way, ſingular, not plurall, <hi>one,</hi> not <hi>more</hi> not many much of the difficulty in the ſouls paſſage to life, would be diſcharged by the multiplicity of pathes: the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger incident to the one, would be avoided by entrance into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46624:9"/> whatſoever be the many ſpecial acts of holineſs, the <hi>Gate of righteouſneſs</hi> is, and can be but <hi>one.</hi> The means whereby to get eternal life is <hi>one</hi> and but <hi>one:</hi> in its general nature, it is ſpecial, it is ſingular: you may obſerve they are predicated by unites, <hi>one</hi> God, <hi>one</hi> Lord, <hi>one</hi> Faith, <hi>one</hi> Baptiſme, <hi>one</hi> Body, and <hi>one</hi> Spirit,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.4, 5.</note> and indeed the ſpeciality of it is fixed in <hi>one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> who ſayeth of himſelf <hi>I am the Way:</hi> and well ſayeth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Chriſt is not divided;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 14.10:</note> Chriſt may be <hi>differently diſpenſed</hi> by doctrines of <hi>Faith,</hi> different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ordinances for worſhip and directions unto duty, <hi>different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exhibited</hi> in his different <hi>natures,</hi> God, Man, <hi>Offices,</hi> Prophet,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.13.</note> Prieſt and King, or different <hi>Acts of Med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atorſhip,</hi> as his Incarnation, Converſe among men, obſervation of the Law, death, reſurrection, Aſcention, and interceſſion, or <hi>differently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred,</hi> that is, made known, and exhibited by different Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in reſpect of their <hi>Kinde,</hi> Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors and Teachers, or in reſpect of the different individual <hi>Perſons</hi> under any kind, as <hi>Paul Apollo, Cephas,</hi> and the like; but in theſe; all theſe, or any of theſe, <hi>Chriſt is not divided;</hi> he is and muſt remain whole and entire, the one, onely way to life; Theſe things of Chriſt may be <hi>diſſantin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae,</hi> they are not, they cannot be <hi>oppoſita,</hi> for they then would be inconſiſtent, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive each to other: <hi>A Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand,</hi> Chriſt divided doth ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe to be: they that embrace not Chriſt under all his exhibited acts and Offices, under all his diſpenced O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dinances, Doctrines and directions, in all and every of his Miniſters, enter not the Gate, walk not in the way to eternall life: nor are theſe in any contrary wayes, but the ſame one individual way exiſting in ſo many diſtinct: and different ſteps ſuch who dream of many, not onely different, but directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wayes to Heaven, do and will deceive themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: For that Gate and Way which admitteth no <hi>Tergiverſacion:</hi> nor regreſſe, no diverſion, deviation or ſtepping aſide, on either the right or left hand, and is the ſame to all a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d every Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller, can be but one: to <hi>divide in the way</hi> is ordinarily incident to Saints: but to <hi>divide the way</hi> is inconſiſtent with ſalvation: <hi>I</hi> have often admited, and muſt confeſſe I cannot underſtand that monſtrous charity of our Age, that men ſhould turn backs in doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of faith and Acts of Worſhip, and yet ſhake hands with a friendly confidence of meeting one another in Heaven: to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46624:10"/> conſtitute contrary Churches, conſecrate a contrary Miniſtry, and ſo create a contrary worſhip in the forme (and <hi>Forma dat eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiam,</hi>) though the matter be Gods, and yet expect that men ſhould know them as <hi>Saints,</hi> and call them Heirs of <hi>Salvation,</hi> and conclude them in the Way to heaven, is as much as if men ſhould conclude the ten Tribes, with their new p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieſts worſhiping God according to the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in their new planted Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethell,</hi> were equally related to, intereſted in, and accepted by God as was <hi>Judah,</hi> and thoſe that feared the Lord, and fled from this new contrary courſe of Religion, though for matter Gods own inſtitution: I am ſure the Apoſtle was a ſtranger to this Charity, when he concluded of the Separating Sects in his time, dividing in doctrine, and from the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church;<note place="margin">Coll. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>that they held not the head, by which the body by joints and bands having nouriſhment miniſtred, and knit together, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth with the increaſe of God. I</hi> do not deny but <hi>Joſeph's</hi> brethren may too unnaturally ſtrive in the way to their Father: but if any of them ſtart from or turne out of the way, they are not like to ſee him. <hi>Schiſmes I</hi> grant may be in the Church, and they are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſad, but <hi>Schiſmes from the Church</hi> are immediately ſubvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Salvation: unfitting contentions may ariſe between <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 15.39.</note> unto an undue heat, concerning Society with a defective brother, inſomuch that they may part aſunder the one paſſing to <hi>Cyprus</hi> the other to <hi>Gilicia,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet both may meet in Heaven: But <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> Contrariety to the courſe of Chriſtianity in a ſlaviſh compliance with the Circumciſion, is to be contradicted by a zealous <hi>Paul</hi> as deſtructive to ſalvation:<note place="margin">Gal. 2.11 12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>I withſtood him to the face, for he was to be blamed becauſe he walked not uprightly, according to the truth of the Goſpel. Hooper</hi> &amp; <hi>Ridley</hi> may with two much heat expoſtulate the retaining Popiſh rites &amp; Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies appendant to Religion in the reformed Church &amp; yet agree in the ſtraite and fiery pſſage to heaven But <hi>Saunders</hi> cannot in charity hope in heaven to meet <hi>Pendleton</hi> turning back upon the Truth, or <hi>Grinwald</hi> who would not pledge him in the Cup of his Martyrdome fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the truth of the Goſpell: <hi>I</hi> deſire to have Charity towards all men, but Charity muſt operate in due &amp; proper Acts, according to the quality of the Object, the charity which commend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth countenanceth &amp; concludeth certainty of life unto the many wanderers out of heavens way, in the by-pathes of their own fancy and humour, unto the contradiction of the Truth, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46624:10"/> caſting off Gods Ordinances, and Goſpell miniſtry, and cutting themſelves off from the communion of the Church, is a <hi>fooliſh pitty,</hi> inconſiſtent with the knowledg of Gods order for mans ſalvation: ſuch as make many and contrary wayes to Heaven, may make a noiſe and profeſſions of holineſs in the world, but will in the end find themſelves miſtaken and others by them miſguided unto the loſſe of eternall life, unto which there is but a Gate, a Way, one <hi>ſingle Gate, and Strait way,</hi> not to be declined: It is indeed true, the heavenly City is ſaid to have <hi>twelve Gates,</hi> but we muſt obſerve this City is the end, not Gate of the Chriſtians journey. The <hi>City of life,</hi> to which the narrow way doth lead, and the multiplicity of theſe Gates, are Meta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>horically mentioned to am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plify the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ory thereof: Mans dignity is ample, and abundant, free and full; but mans duty is auxious and afflicted, ſtrait and narrow; all that enter into the City with 12. open gates, muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the one <hi>Strait gate;</hi> and travell in the one <hi>Narrow way,</hi> which leadeth thereunto: ſuch as walk at large in ſight of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will find themſelves locked out of this glorious palace, when their paſt profeſſions of Chriſt will make them think it hard.</p>
            <p>I have done with the Subject or thing ſpoken of <hi>(viz.)</hi> the means of mans Salvation, <hi>the Gate, the way to life:</hi> I muſt now paſſe unto the Predicate or thing ſpoken of this Gate and Way,<note place="margin">The predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</note> and that is, it is <hi>Strait and narrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This predicate doth declare the property of the paſſage unto Glory: <hi>it is ſtrait &amp; narrow</hi> or as ſome, <hi>ſtrait &amp; low: cloſe &amp; little,</hi> as others or <hi>ſerious, &amp; ſorrowful:</hi> ſay others It is a Metaphor made uſe of, to make knwon the <hi>Difficulty,</hi> &amp; <hi>Danger</hi> which doth attend Travellors in the Way to life &amp; happineſs, as a ſtrait Gate cannot be entered with eaſe nor without ſtooping, and many times Stripping a mans ſelf of all things ſuperfluous, and many times many things neceſſary; nor can men walk in a narrow way with any great pleaſure or free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, no not without ſtriving and preſſing many times, to the pinching of their bodyes and perplexing their mind how to paſs forward, and make their way through unto the attainment of the deſired end, and an arrivall at their intended places of life, and reſt: ſuch is mans eſtate in the uſe of the means of Grace for the obtainment of Glory, in his entrance into and walking in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord: Heaven is not had with ſo much eaſe as moſt men imagine, and the light negligent carriage of too many
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46624:11"/> Chriſtians gives men cauſe to think. Religion is not a buſineſs of ſuch facility to follow and maintain, as many dream and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; a Chriſtians Converſation is not ſo ſmooth and current as many do conceive: Oh no: the Gate of righteouſneſs is more <hi>ſtrait,</hi> the way of holineſs is mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>narrow:</hi> ſuch who will enter it muſt ſtrip themſelves of all ſuperfluities of ſin, and worldly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; they muſt eaſt off the works of darkneſs, and a l that ſin which <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpaſſeth then about,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> and caſt abroad their worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts being read to diſtribute,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17, 18, 19.</note> willing to communicate, ſelling that which they have to give unto the poor: ſometimes the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage may be ſo ſtrait, that they muſt ſtrip themſelves of their very neceſſaries, Lands, Livings, Friends, Houſes, Brethren, Siſters, Wife, Children, and Life it ſelf (without which they cannot praiſe God, nor p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs in the way to life.) Lying dead in the way by preſſing for motion, and progreſs in the courſe of Chriſtianity, is many times the event of the Saints labour, and their actual for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal entrance into the City of life: nor doth the <hi>ſtraitneſs</hi> of this gate, or <hi>narrowneſs</hi> of this way; call for, and more neceſſitate the ſoul to be thus <hi>ſtripped,</hi> then that when thus it do alſo <hi>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op,</hi> bow down, bend unto the very duſt, and creep on its very belly: the <hi>will</hi> muſt be ſubdued unto, reſigned up to <hi>Gods will,</hi> in doing, in ſuffering: <hi>Thy will be done</hi> is the Childes only cry; and in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens way we muſt become Children,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.7.</note> little Children: Mans <hi>reaſon</hi> muſt be reſigned up to <hi>divine Revelation:</hi> The wicked man muſt <hi>forſake his own thoughts,</hi> as well as the unrighteous man his wayes: <hi>Naamans</hi> proud heart muſt ſtoop to the Prophets counſel, and waſh in <hi>Jordan,</hi> or he muſt not loſe his Leproſie: Gods Word muſt caſt down every <hi>imagination,</hi> and every <hi>high thing which exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.5.</note> 
               <hi>and bring into captivity every thought unto the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> Whoſoever will walk with God, muſt <hi>walk humbly with God;</hi> Chriſtians in heavens way muſt like Chriſt, <hi>ſtoop at Gods</hi> will under the rage of men, bow down under the fury of the Oppreſſor, and let the wicked paſſe over them: they muſt ſometimes give their <hi>back to the ſmiters,</hi> and <hi>their cheeks to them who pluck off the hair:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 50.6.</note> they muſt not hide <hi>their face from ſhame and ſpitting;</hi> they muſt in many perplexities paſſe into the poſſeſſion of Life and Glory: Heavens way is not high enough for ſinfull man to ſtand upright in: they muſt proceed with pain and grief, affliction, and anxiety: for <hi>ſtrait
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46624:11"/> is the gate, and narrow is the way which leadeth unto life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Gate is ſaid to be ſtrait, and this way narrow, in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, or for many reaſons, which the learned do obſerve upon this Text: as becauſe it is <hi>repugnant to mans reaſon, diſtaſtful to mans luſt, and affections, attended with diſtreſs, great and many a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>flicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> every of theſe reaſons are true, and good demonſtrations of the difficulty of mans ſalvation: but I ſhall not inſiſt upon them, but propoſe to your conſideration one which is more proper, and is moſt ſpecially intended in the Text.</p>
            <p>Strait is the gate, and narrow is the way to life, for it is <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, limited, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unded;</hi> and <hi>reſtrained;</hi> this gate and way is an <hi>Encloſure,</hi> on each ſide of which are <hi>Bounds</hi> which cannot be broken. without danger; there are <hi>Limitations</hi> which cannot be left in ſafety: and this is the reaſon of all that difficulty and danger, anguiſh, affliction, to which men are expoſed, becauſe they muſt walk, move forward within ſuch <hi>ſtrait bounds,</hi> and <hi>narrow Limits,</hi> and may not, cannot with any ſafety turn back, or turn aſide, when once entred into this ſtrait gate and narrow way.</p>
            <p>Mans invention is indeed a large Field, and common Road; but Gods will is a <hi>ſtrait gate and narrow way:</hi> that once revealed, man is by and to it reſtrained, and may not turn aſide from it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the right hand, or to the left: mans paſſage towards heaven is like unto the paſſage into a priſon, or rather a Palace, where the entertainment is by a low, little Wicket, to which men muſt ſtoop, and in which they cannot enter with any thing ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: and the progreſs is over a narrow Bridge open on both ſides, on which if a man do not move with caution and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, and tread with even ſteps, he will tumble into the ditch; one wry ſtep may prove his ruine. <hi>Holineſs</hi> is like <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s motion to kill the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> upon an high rock, by a narrow path, on each ſide of which is a precipice, and in which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go but muſt creep on their hands and knees: <hi>Godlineſs</hi> is a moſt regular militation, in which the Soldiers are kept cloſe to order, commiſſion and inſtructions not to move one foot without or beyond the ſame. <hi>Mareſcallo</hi> the French General
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46624:12"/> firſt Knighted a Scotch Soldier for an eminent ſervice he had done, and then beheaded him, <hi>for doing it without C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmiſſion;</hi> and the ſame God who bleſſed the houſe of <hi>Obed-Edom</hi> for entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Arke, made a <hi>Perez <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> for <hi>Vzza</hi>'s preſuming <hi>irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to uphold it</hi> when ſhaken in the Cart, and in danger to fall; <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity</hi> in <hi>Sanctity</hi> is a moſt ſtrait line in which no part is crooked; an upright man goeth right forward in Gods way, without bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on either hand; <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is a clear Criticiſme; true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is reduced to a narrow point; theſe are on both hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet with ſin; good is the Councell of Wiſdome, <hi>turne not to the right or left hand, remove thy foot from evil, Pro.</hi> 4.2. What the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then conclude of morall virtue, is moſt true of Chriſtian Graces <hi>(in medio conſiſtit virtus)</hi> true virtue is the narrow midle way, the extreams of which in defect or exceſſe are manifeſt and notorious vice: It is all one in nature to ſhoot ſhort, or wide of the marke; to be daſhed on <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lla</hi> or <hi>Charybdis,</hi> to looſe Salvation by propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or ſuperſtition; to ſubvert the faith, by ignorance or error; to root up the Church by perſecution or ſeperation; to deſtroy Gods worſhip by Irreligion or innovation to walk evenly, to ſail ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily between thoſe extreams, and works which are on each hand, <hi>hic labor, hoc opus,</hi> is an hard piece of work, which will cauſe much care, charge and pains.</p>
            <p>I cannot but obſerve the Scripture Record doth repreſent the Saints integrity to have been prooved, and approved by an exact obedience in ſome narrow Criſis, ſpecial Act, and particuler point, in which they were moſt cloſely Pinched: The whole Law was too large a field for mans obedience in innocency his willing ſubjection to the ſoveraign power of his Creator, muſt be proved by the pinch of <hi>one forbidden tree,</hi> whilſt all in their firſt creation were appointed, and all others were left common, and free unto his uſe. <hi>Noah</hi> muſt be the <hi>Preacher of righteouſneſs</hi> by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the <hi>Arke</hi> (an improbable inſtrument to ſave him, when the floods ſhould over-whelm Houſes, and mountains) <hi>Abraham</hi> may follow God he knows not whether, but muſt be approved the <hi>Father of the faithful,</hi> by <hi>hoping above hope,</hi> unto the ſacrificing of his ſon <hi>Iſaac:</hi> we have heard of the <hi>patience of Job,</hi> which is onely remarkable in one point, he <hi>charged not God fooliſhly;</hi> we have alſo heard of the paſſions of <hi>Job,</hi> he curſed the day of his birth, but he <hi>curſed not his God;</hi> he challenged, but he charged not the Lord! <hi>Davids faith</hi> was approved by his loyalty, his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46624:12"/> head was in his hand, when his heart ſmote him for cutting off the Lap of his garment; what ſhall I tell you of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> of the three Children, of the whole cloud of witneſſes, whoſe faith is found ſincere by a ſingle point of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. Chriſtianity is a moſt narrow Criſis, and muſt be well and warily di cerned; I cannot but wonder to hear ſome men when convincingly pinched by a diſtinct diſcovery of their devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation from truth, and piety, cry out againſt <hi>diſtinctions</hi> as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian and impious: tell them they muſt diſcern between Churches, Miniſters, Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tiſmes; for theſe contradictions, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Conſtitutions cannot be Chriſtian, and carry to heaven; they will call off all poſſibility of conviction by crying out againſt <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gicall diſtinctions in matters of Religion;</hi> I muſt tell ſuch in, no caſe doth that Rule <hi>(Qui bene diſtinguit, bene docet)</hi> diſtinction is mans direction, hold good ſo much as in the caſe of Religion and Salvation, which is many times won or loſt, upon a nice and narrow point, <hi>eating</hi> or not <hi>eating</hi> an Apple, <hi>butchering</hi> or not <hi>butchering</hi> an only Son ſuch who pretend to move in heavens way without <hi>diſtinction,</hi> march with confidence, and ſecurity to deſtruction; diſtinction is the <hi>ratio formalis</hi> of the ſtrait gate, and narrow way; no difficulty, no danger in a way, which needeth no <hi>diſtinction;</hi> ſaving Grace is a <hi>diſcerning Spirit;</hi> the ſpiritual man is a <hi>diſcerner of the things of God; diſtinction</hi> is the onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of ſincerity, and ſoundneſs in the faith; <hi>Hereſies muſt come, that they who are ſound may be made manifeſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19. Iohn. 10.</note> my ſheep <hi>know my voice,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; The devil is often turned into an Angel of light to engage the Elect of God to careful conſiderate diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> ſhall ſometimes tempt the <hi>diſtinguiſhing power of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods people; true piety muſt be approved,</hi> by a nick, or nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row point of obedience in every condition, and relation, avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all <hi>deviations,</hi> as well as <hi>defects,</hi> and this cannot be obſerved if not <hi>diſcerned;</hi> there is a <hi>ſimplicity of the Goſpel,</hi> from to which we muſt not be beguiled, <hi>a truth of the Goſpel</hi> according to which we muſt walk with right ſteps, the outlet of <hi>diſtinction,</hi> is the inlet of <hi>deluſion;</hi> neglect to <hi>diſcern the truth</hi> that you may embrace it in the love of it; and you ſhall eaſily <hi>believe lyes:</hi> the Cautions in Scripture are to no purpoſe to men who caſt off diſtinction; <hi>take heed what you hear, beware of the leaven of the Phariſees,</hi> and the like, are inſignificant directions to men of no <hi>diſtinction:</hi> the neglect
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46624:13"/> of <hi>diſtinction,</hi> will make <hi>Peter a ſinfull Conformiſt,</hi> as well as thoſe pointed at in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10 25. were <hi>ſinfull non-communicants:</hi> there is no eſtate in which we are in the world, which is not on both hands bounded with ſin: are we <hi>Proſperous?</hi> it is a narrow point to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Creatures of God with thanksgiving, to uſe them humbly and with ſobriety, not unto pride and tyranny, ſecurity and carnall confidence, in the caſting off God, or contempt of our brethren: with <hi>diſcretion</hi> to eſteem, enjoy, and uſe them as <hi>Gods good bleſſings,</hi> and yet not to abuſe them to the ſatisfaction of our ſenſual luſt, and the entangling of our ſouls in ſin: How Hard do we find it, in the day of affliction, and diſtreſſe, to ſhun ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſenſeleſſe <hi>Apathie,</hi> Stoicall <hi>ſtupidity,</hi> and impatient <hi>anxiety,</hi> peircing grief or fear, heart-perplexing, God-provoking <hi>Cares</hi> and <hi>Complaints,</hi> not to lay aſide, nor let our naturall paſſions break out, beyond the bounds of ſobriety, reaſon or Religion: to fear without <hi>fretting</hi> diſcerne danger without <hi>diffidence,</hi> to be angry without <hi>envy,</hi> to grieve without grudging: to mourn with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>murmuring,</hi> to be ſtricken and ſmitten of God, afflicted all the day long, and lye in ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, without <hi>repining</hi> or <hi>charging God fooliſhly:</hi> or charging piety to be <hi>perplexing folly:</hi> but to lay our Mouthes in the duſt under our opreſſed innocency, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Lord hath done it:</hi> to be reviled of men, and not to <hi>revile again:</hi> to be oppreſſed and perſecuted, yet <hi>free from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge:</hi> to bleſſe them that <hi>curſe us,</hi> and pray for them who <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully uſe us,</hi> is a leſſon not eaſily learned: truly friends, my experience hath found it a ſtrait Gate, a narrow way, to retain <hi>quick and lively ſences,</hi> under the reſtraint of a <hi>lively faith:</hi> to fear and grieve, and yet not <hi>fly</hi> in the face of men, or forget God: I cannot but obſerve <hi>Apathy</hi> in afflictions is manifeſt prophaneſſe:<note place="margin">Iſa. 42.25</note> and impatiency is no leſſe then impiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: God aggravateth <hi>Iſrael</hi> prophaneſſe by their Stupidity and ſhamefull <hi>Apathy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>when he ſet them on fire round about, they knew it n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t:</hi> It <hi>burned them and they layed it not to heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa 22.12 13, 14.</note> he obſerveth as an argument of inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility under his hand: He complaineth of them, as impudently impious, becauſe when they were <hi>ſtriken they did not grieve:</hi> He chargeth it as an inniquity indelible to be merry and jovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in Feaſts, and full expreſſions of joy, when his providence and their perplexing ſtate doth call <hi>for weeping and mourning:</hi> and on the other hand he rebuketh exceſſe of paſſion as no leſſe prophane:<note place="margin">Iſa. 15.12 13.</note> 
               <hi>Who Art thou that art affraid of the fury of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:46624:13"/> and <hi>forgeteſt the Lord thy maker: not</hi> to <hi>fear</hi> is <hi>inhumane;</hi> to fear <hi>without faith,</hi> is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian;</hi> not to <hi>care</hi> is contrary to reaſon, to care unto <hi>vexations diffidence,</hi> concerning future events, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to true <hi>Religion; not to mourn</hi> in, miſery is incongruous to <hi>men,</hi> (Subjects of ſence and reaſon) to <hi>mourn as without hope</hi> is incongruous to <hi>Chriſtans,</hi> in whom reaſon is rectifyed, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to expectation of a better change. The nature of patience doth charge ſin on both extreams, it preſuppoſeth, it preſerveth paſſions exiſtent; whilſt it aboundeth, reſtraineth, regulateth the ſame; we have heard of the <hi>paſſions of Job;</hi> I could never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the patience, and meekneſs of Malefactors, who ſuffered the utmoſt ſorrows, under the greateſt, moſt manifeſt Guilt, without the leaſt of grief, or fear, commotion of mind or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing apprehenſion; Yea under the greateſt oſtentation of joy &amp; peace, being cannonized by their friends for Martyrs, on the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ground of their confidence: which (to the Blaſphemy of Chriſtianity and its Martyrs) they call Chriſtian courage, ſure <hi>I</hi> am that they who rejoyced with joy <hi>unſpeakable and full of Glory,</hi> beleiving in whom <hi>they had not ſeen,</hi> were <hi>in heavineſe</hi> under all kind of grief, <hi>through manifold temptations;</hi> and they who truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the living God, who had delivered, and would deliver were by the power of their paſſions <hi>preſſed out of meaſure,</hi> and <hi>above their Strength;</hi> a due deportment in every condition as men, and Chriſtians, is a <hi>narrow ſtrait,</hi> an eſtate of great difficulty and danger; the ſame bounds and ſtrait Limitts attend our relation and the dutyes thereof; How hard for <hi>Subjects</hi> (as ſincere <hi>David</hi>) to retain Loyalty and affection towards oppreſſing perſecuteing Princes? How hard for <hi>Servants</hi> to be ſubject to their Maſters, not onely the meek and gentle, but alſo to the froward? to do well and ſuffer for it patiently, is an hard ſaying, who can bear it: This <hi>Straitneſs</hi> attends our whole Converſation, and the courſe of our lives in common as Chriſtians; to continue <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſts Church,</hi> under many and great <hi>Corrupcions,</hi> and not to <hi>comply</hi> with and <hi>conforme,</hi> unto ſinfull impoſitions; not to <hi>leave</hi> Gods Ordinances when made <hi>grievious</hi> to the Soul by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Appendants, and diſorder, not to <hi>ceaſe</hi> the offerings of the Lord, when the prophaneſs and violent diſorder of the <hi>Sons of Elie</hi> make them <hi>loath</hi> the ſame; to <hi>hear</hi> them who <hi>ſay,</hi> but do not; onely becauſe they are in <hi>Moſes chair.</hi> to beware of the leaven of the Phariſes, being bound to <hi>hear them,</hi> who ordinarily teach for doctrines the <hi>traditions of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46624:14"/> men,</hi> and make the <hi>word of God of none effect:</hi> to retain <hi>Church uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> under its impurity, and attend <hi>Goſpel-miniſtry</hi> in prophane ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; to be zealous for <hi>reformation,</hi> without running into, or ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hands with ſeparation, is, <hi>hic labor hoc opus</hi> to religious hearts who walk uprightly according to the truth of the Goſpel, a <hi>ſtrait gate,</hi> a <hi>narrow way,</hi> a narrow Criſis and point of duty, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be declined without danger, ſin lying on both hands, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or exceſs to deſtroy us: the way to heaven is apparently ſtrait and narrow, becauſe thus <hi>bounded and terminated;</hi> and for this reaſon our Saviour doth declare it ſo to be.</p>
            <p>In this Sermon, our Saviour doth direct exact obedience into a narrow Criſis, and place <hi>perfection</hi> in a ſtrait punctilio: The ſcope and drift of the Sermon is to ſhew the bounds and limits of the way of life, the reſtraints of Religion, which the error and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of the Jews had broken down, to the facilitating of their paſſage to Heaven.</p>
            <p>His moſt pleaſing <hi>Preface</hi> propoundeth <hi>poverty of Spirit, mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, meekneſs, purity</hi> and <hi>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ution,</hi> and the like perplexing proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as Conditions of the <hi>Beatitudes</hi> he doth declare: His <hi>directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> unto duty begin with a determination of dread, <hi>He that break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the leaſt of theſe Commandements ſhall be leaſt in the kingdome of Heaven:</hi> and ſo proceeding to terminate duty by a clear expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law, he placeth the breach of the Law in a little, narrow point. Murther he determineth in a <hi>ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnful word in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture:</hi> Adultery in the <hi>caſt of the eye:</hi> Diſobedience in the <hi>neglect of a parent</hi> prophaning Gods Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in a groundleſs and <hi>trivial Oath:</hi> the whole matters of his Sermon are moſt ſtrict Rules, in the obſervation whereof he placeth perfection, in ſimilitude to God: and in this very Text the <hi>ſtrait</hi> is oppoſed to the <hi>wide Gate,</hi> the <hi>narrow</hi> to the <hi>broad way,</hi> the way of ſin is an open Common, the champian ground, in which the mighty Hunters againſt the Lord doe ſport themſelves without any limits: but the way of Sanctity is an Encloſure, a paſſage perillous, fickle, difficult, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, in which men cannot move without fear and care, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pain and grief, without croſſes and loſſes, without ſmart and ſuffering, without preſſing and ſtriving, and yet out of it they may not turn to right or left hand without certain ruine.</p>
            <p>The way to Heaven is a red Sea paſſage, in which there is no poſſibility of motion unto ſafety and life, but by going forward; for enemies are behind, and walls of water doe on each fide en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe us, if we give back the enemies will deſtroy us, we cannot
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46624:14"/> ſtep aſide but the Sea will drown us; by going forward we may meet with a wilderneſs march, and many encounters with the ſons of <hi>Anack,</hi> and the Kings of the Countries through which we travel: but we are ſure at laſt to arrive at the Land of life and promiſe, for <hi>ſtrait is the gate and narrow is the way, which leadeth unto life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the explication of this Propoſition: before I paſs to application, I ſhall note and but note unto you the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which doe convincingly demonſtrate that <hi>ſtrait is the gate,</hi> and <hi>narrow is the way which leadeth unto life,</hi> and I ſhall not wander to ſeek them, they are ſuggeſted in the Text, and are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Life is the end</hi> unto which this way doth lead, and that you <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> heard before is an <hi>eſtate of excellency,</hi> its obtainment and effecting muſt needs be by <hi>means of intricacy; difficulty</hi> is inſeparably atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on <hi>dignity:</hi> the paſſage into a Princes Pallace is not common or eaſie, but by many ſtrait gates and dark entries: Pebbles lye common on the ſurface of the earth, but Pearles are hidden in the bowels thereof, and muſt be digged out with difficulty and danger: Needs there be any more ſaid to convince you, that Grace and Holineſs is a <hi>ſtrait gate</hi> and <hi>narrow way,</hi> then to tell you it <hi>leadeth unto glory:</hi> this eſtate was not purchaſed without the Lord Jeſus coming from Heaven, being tempted by the Devil, tormented by men, forſaken by God, and his paſſing through the ſtraits of a ſhameful curſed death: and can we think it ſhould lie common and open without guard or encloſure, for any that will, when they will, which way they will to enter into? It is below its worth, and ſhould expoſe it unto contem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t.</p>
            <p>This Gate and way is ſtrait and narrow, becauſe ſingular 'tis <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> one, and 'tis but one. In this way we muſt go to Heaven, and out of this way we cannot get to Heaven; ſingularity is alway attended with difficulty; be this way never ſo foul &amp; tireſom, never ſo tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and troubleſom, we have no other way in which we can walk to this end: all confinement is croſs to mans ſpirit: How are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en affrighted from, and afflicted in the wayes of godlineſs, becauſe of reproach of ſingularity? which ſhould be rather their induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and encouragement to perſeverance with all diligence; for the Heirs of Heaven are ſingulars, not <hi>every one</hi> that cryeth <hi>Lord, Lord:</hi> the way to Heaven is ſingular, but one encloſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſcribed way, though our corrupt nature be diſpoſed to run at liberty, and prophaneſs will bear no reſtraint, yet we muſt know we muſt keep cloſe to Gods Commandements, and walk in the one way, the one
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46624:15"/> Gate of his appointment unto life. Nature hath made many wayes to death, and but one way of difficulty and danger to paſſe into life, and corrupt nature can and doth create many wayes to Hel: but the guift of God is eternall life, to be obtained in, and by that <hi>one,</hi> and <hi>only way,</hi> which he hath determinated bounded and revealed.</p>
            <p>This Gate and way to life is ſtrait, and <hi>narrow,</hi> becauſe <hi>few <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> there be that find it</hi> paucity of Travellors does make, as well as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim difficulty in the way of motion: for becauſe <hi>few</hi> paſſe through it, it is <hi>untract, untrodden,</hi> not eaſily to be diſcerned: Chriſts flock is a <hi>litle flock,</hi> the Elect are but a <hi>remnant:</hi> there are but a <hi>few names</hi> who are found faithfull: many may follow Chriſt but there are few will ſell that they have, and give to the poor ſome will deny themſelves, take up their croſſe and follow him many will call him Lord, Lord, but <hi>few</hi> will do what he ſaith: many may ſtrive to enter in at the Strait Gate, but few are able to effect it: nor is there any more plain and clear demonſtration of difficulty and danger then the paucity of thoſe who paſſe through it: a common Road, is a beaten Road, every man will travel the open way, few will take pains to paſſe through ſtraits to the poſceſſions of life and glory.</p>
            <p>This gate ie a ſtrait, this way is narrow, for there is in it no entrance, no proceſſe without <hi>diligence.</hi> our Saviour did direct his curioniſts queſtions <hi>to ſtrive to enter</hi> in at the ſtrait gate, but <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>4</label> this puts me upon the application.</p>
            <p>The Application of this Doctrine might be large, and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> but time will not allow me to expatiate: but doth conſtrain me to contract <hi>I</hi> will therefore paſſe by thoſe many Inferences which flow from hence, and confine my ſelfe to my Text, and our Saviours method <hi>(viz.)</hi> an <hi>exhortation,</hi> affectionately to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and earneſtly to preſſe forward in the ſtrait gate and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way.</p>
            <p>My beloved, be intreated ſeriouſly to reflect upon your thought, s <hi>that ſtrait is the Gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth unto life,</hi> and let difficulty, perſuade, provoke your diligence conſider the words and exhortation of our Saviour, <hi>enter in at the ſtrait gate, and narrow way,</hi> ſo our Evangeliſts, doth report it: but Luke reporteth it, <hi>ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait Gate:</hi> The duty is the ſame in both theſe Evangeliſts, though the different occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46624:15"/> on which it was perſwaded, cauſed ſome difference in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; but both the ſentences are conſiderable and have their Empha as St. <hi>Ma.</hi> preſents it to us; it guideth our <hi>choice</hi> &amp; affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to <hi>embrace:</hi> according to St. <hi>Luke,</hi> it provoketh our <hi>induſtry</hi> in purſuit of our choſen object, that we may not miſs to attain the end: enter in at the ſtrait gate, that is, <hi>chuſe,</hi> and affectionately embrace the way of danger and difficulty, in which you cannot move without eare and coſt, without courage and conſideration, without preſſing and perplexity; although your nature cannot but affect eaſe, deſire to walk at large, reluct under the very thoughts of reſtraint, and regulation: be wiſe, be well adviſed by me (ſaith our Saviour) who have, and know the iſſues of life and death, to deny your ſelves, and direct your feet into the ſoul way, <hi>ſtrait g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e and nar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w paths:</hi> caſt your ſelves under divine directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; paſſe your lives in an exact obſervancy of divine preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; receive the yoak, abide the bonds of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; decline the way with, and in which fleſh and blood is ſo much, ſo well pleaſed, and reſign up your mind, will, affections, actions and paſſions, to the reſtraints of Reaſon, to the regulation of Religion: anſwerable to this Exhortation is our Saviours Argument, drawn from the <hi>end</hi> unto which this ſtrait gate doth lead: <hi>It leadeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life:</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, you ſee before you different paths, you are to make your choice, be by me adviſed to conſider, that <hi>broad way, and wide gate, leadeth to deſtruction;</hi> but this <hi>ſtart gate and narrow way leadeth unto life:</hi> guide therefore your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the end you aim at, and enter in at the ſtrait Gate. I this day ſet before you life and death, chuſe you which you will take: I cannot but tell you, if you embrace the <hi>broad way,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the multitude to do evil, pleaſe your own luſts, and live as you liſt, without regard to, or reſtraint by Gods holy Word, you ſhall enjoy <hi>preſent caſe,</hi> and <hi>future endleſs miſery:</hi> but if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline this broad way, and enter the ſtrait Gate, deny your ſelves, enter the way of Gods Commandements, and walk uprightly in them, not turning aſide to the right or left hand, you muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed undergo preſent hardſhip, but ſhall hereby attain unto, arrive at eternal happineſs.</p>
            <p>Let the end, the laſt in your enjoyment be the firſt thing in your intention, and you cannot ſtick in your thoughts what to chuſe: who will not labour for life, rather then lie ſtill and die? Who will not paſs ſome ſtraits to poſſeſs ſuch glory, rather then live in pleaſure and loſe ſalvation for ever? who at the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46624:16"/> will not chuſe the portion of <hi>Lazarus</hi> before that of <hi>Dives?</hi> How ſad a check is it to <hi>Dives</hi> comforts to hear the Lord ſay, <hi>Thou haſt now thy good things, but ſhalt he hereafter tormented?</hi> How reviving refreſhing is it to poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to know the Lord looketh on his low eſtate, and reſolveth, that <hi>he, in this life afflicted,</hi> ſhall be in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams boſome abundantly comforted,</hi> coſt what it can, be it never ſo ſtrait and narrow, enter in at the ſtrait gate, it <hi>leadeth unto life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to St. <hi>Luke, Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate;</hi> enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, for <hi>life</hi> is the end of it, ſtrive unto this entrance for you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for <hi>life,</hi> and that calleth for the utmoſt diligence and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of endeavours: <hi>ſtrive</hi> not feebly and faintly, but with force and vigor; preſs forward in it with ſtrength and vivacity, with power unto perplexity: ſtrive unto, and again, until you ſweat, until you bleed again, preſs into this narrow paſſage, until you be immured and periſh, if need ſo require: ſtretch your limb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> until you be not able to ſtand; walk with, wait on God, untill and after you are weary: you cannot live with God unleſs you love God, you cannot love God unleſs you embrace him: purſue him with <hi>all your heart,</hi> with <hi>all your might,</hi> with <hi>all your ſoul,</hi> with <hi>all your ſtrength:</hi> you ſeek ſalvation, though it is not wages, you muſt work for it, <hi>work out your own ſalvation with fear and trembling,</hi> with a fear of diligence, not of diffidence and deſpondency: a ſight of <hi>Iſraels</hi> glory will make a curſing <hi>Balaam</hi> cry out, <hi>Oh that I might die the death of the righteous, and that my latter end might be like his:</hi> but the <hi>laborious life</hi> of the righteous can only ſecure the <hi>happy death</hi> which paſſeth into <hi>eternal life.</hi> Heaven is not had with a wet finger: ſhort winded wiſhes will never ſet any in the haven of everlaſting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs: the ſlothful in Chriſtianity can never inherit the promiſe the kingdome of Heaven ſuffers violence, the <hi>violent take it by force fight</hi> ſo as to get victory, ſo <hi>run</hi> as to obtain, ſo <hi>wreſtle</hi> as to prevail, ſo <hi>ſtrive</hi> as to be able to enter the ſtrait gate, for <hi>ſtrait is the gate and narrow is the way that leadeth unto life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave to inforce this general Exhortation, unto an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious preſſing on in holineſs, and heavens way, by ſome fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> motives, which may perſwade with you, and make you ſee the neceſſity thereof.</p>
            <p>Conſider therefore:</p>
            <p>Heavens way is an <hi>hard way,</hi> it is a way of <hi>difficulty,</hi> muſt be walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in with diligence: it is a way of <hi>danger,</hi> muſt be traverſed with care: 'tis a way of <hi>dolour</hi> and diſtreſs muſt be moved in with <hi>delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> and <hi>diſcretion:</hi> Heavens way is an hard way, becauſe as you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46624:16"/> have heard it is <hi>terminated</hi> and <hi>bound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> out of which there is no ſtarting on either ſide, with the leaſt of ſafety: Beſides that, 'tis thus hard in it ſelf, it is made more hard by theſe things which attend it, or rather <hi>us</hi> in the entrance into this <hi>Strait Gate:</hi> and <hi>narrow way</hi> for it is to every the Sons of men.</p>
            <p>A way of <hi>obſcurity;</hi> hard to <hi>finde out,</hi> hard to be <hi>travelled in,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heavens way ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure.</note> it is a <hi>Miſtery: Great is the miſtery of Godlineſſe: Miſteries</hi> are not eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, it is a peculiar priviledge, a ſpecial favour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a guift from heaven, from God,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>to know the miſteries of the Kingdome of Heaven:</hi> this is not obivious to every eye; <hi>the natural man receiveth not the things of God, for they are ſpecially diſcerned:</hi> this way obſcure in it ſelf is <hi>untrodden,</hi> few there be who find it:<note place="margin">Mat. 13.11. 1 Cor. 2.14.</note> the tract is <hi>ſmall and litle,</hi> not eaſily diſcerned the <hi>footſteps found,</hi> are to be followed, but their impreſſion is ſo litle that they are ſoon worn out: Examples of exact obedience are very <hi>few:</hi> one <hi>Noah</hi> ſerving providence in the means of his own appointment, is the <hi>Preacher of Righteouſneſs:</hi> to the old world, one <hi>Abraham</hi> is the patterne of <hi>perfect reſignation</hi> to God a ſufficient: one <hi>Moſes</hi> for <hi>meekneſſe;</hi> one <hi>Iob,</hi> for <hi>patience,</hi> one <hi>David,</hi> for <hi>Int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g ity,</hi> and ſo ſingular Saints have trodden, the tracts of ſpeciall Graces, in the way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and their footſteps are to be found with moſt diligent ſearch and accurate obſervation: this obſcure and trodden way to life: is perplexed with many <hi>intricacies,</hi> and <hi>doubts,</hi> which do ariſe from the variety of Gods providence, and variation of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition how to carry in a ſingle, how in a married? ho to carry in an adverſe, how in a a proſperous ſtate, how to carry in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and variety of Society? how to carry in ſolitudes? how to live by faith in all conditions? how to live under Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, under all diſpenſations how to do the duty of a Miniſter and of a common member to the Church? How to purſue the purity, and how to preſerve the entity of the Church? how to advance the power of godlineſs? and how to attend and edify our ſelves by Gods Ordinances, under confuſed corrupt diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly prophane adminiſtration? In a word h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w to perceive, and performe the Criſis and Punct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lio of Piety pointed out, and to be put into art by and under the preſent providence, ſo as not to fli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on either hand, are ſuch caſes of conſcience, and doubts of minde which muſt, but cannot (with eaſe, nor without much diligence, and difficulty) be reſolved, for our guidance in the ſtrait narrow pathes, which lead to life and glory.</p>
            <p>Yet again conſider this obſcure, untrodden and perplexed way
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46624:17"/> to Heaven: is more hard to find, to enter, by the many by-pathes and <hi>deluſive deviations</hi> which lye on earth-ſide therof: what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to try the Spirits: many Spirits not being of God, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errors in doctrine, darkning the faith, ſuch ſubtill inſinuations of ſeducers, drawing from the truth that the Miniſters of God cannot b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t fear, the people ſhould be beguiled from ſimplicity of the Goſpell: And the people cannot but find by <hi>Peters</hi> fall, it is an hard matter to walk up rightly according to the truth of the Goſpell, the Devil transforming himſelf into An Angell of light is not ſoon or eaſily diſcerned, or diſcovered, good men may be catched with error, yea <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> goodmen, and <hi>Miniſters may be carried away; with the diſſimulation of ſeducers; for the <hi>falſe Apoſtles appear even as the Apostles Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> obſcurity muſt provoke enquiry and ſerious ſtudy, for the narrow bounds of truth and Piety are not diſcerned, without much difficulty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heavens way oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note>
               <hi>This is a way of no leſſe ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>curity, then <hi>oppoſition:</hi> Chriſtianity is a <hi>conſtant mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> Whatſoever be the mutation of humane affairs in the world the Church of Jeſus Chriſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and muſt be militant; till he come in Glory being entered we make no progreſs in piety without blowes; Godlineſs is the takeing of a Garriſon, the Gate is hardly gained,<note place="margin">Heb: 10.23</note> and that entered; every ſteep in the ſtreets is to follow the ſtroak of a begun victory: <hi>after,</hi> yea immediately after, <hi>they were enlightned, they endured a great fight of afflictions: Iſrae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> poſſeſſeth not the Land of Promiſe but by the perſuit of <hi>Egypt,</hi> paſſage through the Sea, Conflicts with, and unto the Conqueſt of the Sons of <hi>Anak,</hi> and Kings of the Countries: and ſincere Saints muſt cut their wayes to heaven:<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.12.</note> Wreſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng not with fleſh and blood, but againſt <hi>Principalities and pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> againſt the <hi>Rulers of the darkneſs of this world and ſpirituall wickedneſs, in high Places,</hi> ſo ſubtle and many are the temptati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Devil, that it is hard for the moſt ſerious ſoldier under Chriſts Banner to be able to ſtand againſt the <hi>Wiles of th Devil.</hi> Oh ſtrait Gate: Oh narrow way; where our hands muſt h w and cut open the way in which our feet muſt rread; if we will find eternall life: this way is yet the more difficult and ſtrait, beccauſe our d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>praved nature is averſe unto this obſcure, oppoſed way; The natural man is at <hi>emnity with G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d;</hi> mans ſoul cannot receive righteouſneſs, with out reluctancy;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note> holineſs is not only <hi>Supernatural,</hi> and above our reach, but <hi>contronatural</hi> and againſt our diſpoſition, Conſtitution, and Inclination; Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens way is uphill, and againſt heart; we are loath to enter the Gate, and more loath to proceed in the way to life; many ſtrive but are not able to enter we are by nature of dull Capacity to diſcerne sloathfull to endeavour: and therefore move heavily in undertakeing the profeſſion of piety: we are by nature feeble, ready to faint under difficulty; fearfull uf heart ready to fall back, on the firſt aſſaults of oppoſition; we are by nature of a wandring ſpirit ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to go aſtray. <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Schiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> are the fruits of our fleſh; VVe can eaſily deviate into by-pathes,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> turn aſide from the way of truth; a direct Courſe is a matter of great difficulty and much diligence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:46624:17"/>
            <p>Chriſtians, if in good earneſt you ſeek life, you muſt ſtrive, you cannot without great ſtrugling unto and againſt, vanquiſh the difficulties of obſcurity, oppoſition, and your own averſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the way to Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate,</hi> for your entrance is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſably <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive </seg>2</label> neceſſary;</hi> the gate to life is but <hi>one,</hi> and no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into this gate without <hi>ſtriving:</hi> No poſſibility of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but in <hi>Gods way,</hi> be it never ſo contrary to our own will: And ſo narrow is the punctillio of piety, and paſſage to life that a <hi>paſſion,</hi> a point of good manners doth many times divert us, and endanger our ſalvation; <hi>Davids fretting</hi> did almoſt, and <hi>Peters fear</hi> did altogether trip up his heels in the way of truth; he walked not with a right foot: yea <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> good manners muſt be ſometimes rebuked by his Maſters pity, <hi>If I waſh thee not thou haſt no part in me:</hi> Be Gods way never ſo repugnant to reaſon, a proud <hi>Naaman</hi> muſt ſtoop to it, or retain his Leproſie to his ruine; be the gate to heaven never ſo much againſt our Will, we muſt into it, for we have no other way: He that loveth any thing, though life it ſelf, better then Chriſt is not worthy of him. The gate and way to life is moſt certainly, <hi>Cauſa ſive qua non;</hi> if we will not ſtrive we cannot enter; and if we do not ſtrive, let us profeſs Chriſt at what rate we will, and poſſeſs the diſpenſations of Chriſts Goſpel, priviledges of his Church, and preſence, in what meaſure we can; when we would enter life we may knock in vain, for the Lord will proteſt he <hi>knoweth us not,</hi> we were not under his conduct in the way, and may not therefore come into his communion in the end of our Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Strive to enter in at the ſtait gate,</hi> for the <hi>ſucceſs is certain</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive </seg>3</label> unto ſerious and conſtant diligence; your induſtry ſhall be inforced to its end; God is not bound, but he doth not deny his grace to ſuch as ſtrenuouſly, ſtudiouſly preſs in the way of his commandments: This is the Argument by which the Apoſtle perſwadeth diligence and activity for ſalvation, <hi>Work out</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>your own ſalvation, for it is God that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in you to will and to do of his own pleaſure.</hi> Such as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the conflict under Chriſts Banner, ſhall not fail of the conqueſt; ſuch as perſevere in preſſing forward, ſhall find
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46624:18"/> the grace of Chriſt ſufficient for them, until <hi>they apprehend that for which they were apprehended of Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour indeed telleth us, <hi>many did ſtrive but were not able;</hi> but you muſt underſtand it aright, they ſtrove <hi>unto,</hi> not <hi>in the act;</hi> they ſtrove under the pangs of conviction, put forth many good purpoſes; but theſe proved abortive, and never paſſed into act; their hearts were never indeed ſet on God, on Chriſt, on Holineſs; their judgements were herein informed, but their affections were not herein inflamed; for he that hath an heart ſhall never want ſtrength to go to heaven; ſtrive in the entring, proceeding act, and we ſhall prove <hi>he wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath begun his good work ſhall and will perfect it, unto the day of his Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Strive we to enter the ſtrait gate,</hi> for the <hi>end is more worth then the utmoſt of our endeavours;</hi> Heaven will make amends for all the hardſhip of the way thither. How did the Patriarchs preſs on the bare perceptions of faith, <hi>not having received the promiſe</hi> (which we have performed) <hi>but ſeeing them afar off,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13.</note> ſaluting them at a diſtance; our Lord Jeſus hath led us this way, <hi>for the joy which was ſet before him, he endured the croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame.</hi> The conſcience of duty will make a ſincere Saint confeſs, that in the moſt exact of his obedience, he is an <hi>unprofitable ſervant;</hi> but when we ſhall come to make a ſenſible compariſon between the dignity we receive, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence we uſed, the difficulties we felt, we ſhall find cauſe to cry out, <hi>by Grace we are ſaved:</hi> The light and momentany afflictions through which we paſs here, are not to be compared to the exceeding, eternal weight of glory which we ſhall enjoy hereafter. Our preſent preſſing, fighting, ſtriving in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens way may coſt us many a weary ſtep, and weeping eye, many ſighs and groans, many prayers and tears, many care<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and fears, many an aking head and heart: It may coſt us our beſt worldly enjoyments, deareſt Relations, and our very life, but coſt what it will, it can never coſt too dear: If once we arrive at this Haven we ſhall ſit down without the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining, repenting thought that ever it coſt ſo dear; we would not for ten thouſand times as much have loſt eternal life.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Friends, I hope the conſideration of theſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46624:18"/> things will excite your diligence, and provoke you to preſs through the many difficulties and dangers which are in the way to heaven, and ſtir up your ſelves to ſtrive to enter in at the <hi>ſtrait gate,</hi> and go forward in the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arrow way which lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto life.</hi> What now remaineth but that I preſent you with ſome few Directions, which being well obſerved may fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate your paſſage to glory, alleviate your burden, and make Chriſtianity, the courſe of piety, a courſe of more delight and eaſe. Obſerve therefore theſe Rules for your help herein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Go not without God;</hi> march after the Captain of your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>1</label> under the conduct of the Lord of Hoſts; the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God is the prop of the ſoul in all perplexity; the moſt certain protection of his people in all their diſtreſſes and dangers; the only aſſurance and encouragement that God ever gave, or his ſervants ever deſired in all their underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of difficulty and danger was, <hi>his preſence; Jeremiah</hi> muſt ſtand as an iron wall, and pillar of braſs againſt Kings, Princes, Prieſts, Prophets, people, under the alone protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of, <hi>I will be with thee, ſaith the Lord;</hi> So alſo do the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel. <hi>Gods preſence</hi> is the beſt ſecurity in all our ſtraits; his Spirit will guide us into all truth, reſolve all our doubts, and be a voyce unto us ſaying, <hi>This is the way walk in it.</hi> When we are ready to wander on the right or on the left hand, his Providence will ſupply all our wants, his Grace w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ſupport all our weakneſs; in a word, whatſoever be our temptation his wiſdom will find for us a way of eſcape, that we may be able to bear it; for <hi>if God be with us, who can be againſt us?</hi> what can be too hard for us? <hi>I know how to want, and how to abound; I can do all things through Chriſt which ſtrengtheneth me,</hi> was the Apoſtles, and is every Saints experience.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Friends, your progreſs towards heaven is as a Wilderneſs-march to the Land of Promiſe; <hi>ſtir not without God.</hi> Take up <hi>Moſes</hi> reſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, <hi>Verily if thou go not with us, we will not go up hence:</hi> Be not put off with an <hi>Angel,</hi> the Angels are undoubtedly <hi>miniſtring ſpirits to the heirs of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> We owe much to God for the Miniſtry of the Angels,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46624:19"/> 
               <hi>they pitch their tents about them that fear him, and keep them in all their ways.</hi> But (my beloved) the difficulties which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend our ſalvation can only be vanquiſhed by a <hi>Divine Arm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.25.51.14, 15.</note> they are too ſtrong for any created being; to <hi>divide the Sea</hi> when the waves roar upon the Captive exile, haſtening to be delivered, it is the work of the Lord of Hoſts; to take away the <hi>captive from the mighty,</hi> and to deliver the <hi>prey of the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible,</hi> is the proper act of the <hi>mighty God of Jacob.</hi> Move not without God, as ever you mean to move with ſtrength and ſucceſs; for of our ſelves we can do nothing; the Lord is he who worketh our works in us and for us, both to will and to do.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Get and ſtudy a right Map of Heaven;</hi> get the deſcription of the City of life, for the nature and ſcituation thereof will not onely enflame your affections, and add wings to your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, but will help us to gueſs how to ſteer our courſe thitherward: To be well skilled in the Map, is the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of travel: And to have good intelligence of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Quarters, is the great advantage of Warfare: The paths of peace are only made known by <hi>Wiſdom.</hi> The Prince of life can only reveal the ſtate and paſſage unto life: The Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus reſolved his Diſciples to be more then half in Heaven, when he could aſſure them they knew the <hi>place,</hi> and they knew <hi>the way.</hi> My beloved cleave cloſs to the Scriptures, and ſtudy them, they ſhew the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is above, the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Rocks and ſhelves, the Ports, Creeks, Straits and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row paſſages which you paſs; the dangers and difficulties which attend you in your paſſage, the people and Enemies you muſt encounter, and how you may direct your ſelves in all theſe. Chriſtians, know that the light of Nature is too dark to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the dignity or difficulties; the dictates of men, the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Church, the determination of Council, the Laws of Princes, are improper, imperfect directions to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whereby we travel to Heaven. I deſpiſe not thoſe, but give them their due honor: But I would have you to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Iſraels</hi> wilderneſs-march to the Land of promiſe was in every ſtep directed by the <hi>immediate Oracles of God:</hi> And the eie of Faith did direct the Patriarchs through many narrow,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46624:19"/> ſtrait paſſages, to ſeek the City not made with hands, and the Scriptures were written that you may beleive Chriſt is the way, and that by beleiving you may have eternal life, ſearch then the Scriptures, for in them you think, and I am ſure you have eternal life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gain an account what it may coſt you to get to Heaven: Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitus, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>3</label> praemunitus;</hi> a foreſeen Charge is eaſily defrayed; our Saviours Advice is, that we be wiſe Maſter builders, and politique Warriors, to forecaſt, a capacity to effect, before we undertake an enterprize; and to compleat the Fabrick, before we lay the Foundation; he who can account all things <hi>loſs and dung</hi> in compariſon of Chriſt, will eaſily inſult over difficulty in Heavens way, and triumphantly reſolve <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtreſs,</hi> nor <hi>tribulation,</hi> nor <hi>perſecution,</hi> nor <hi>peril,</hi> nor <hi>ſword,</hi> nor <hi>famine,</hi> nor <hi>nakedneſs,</hi> ſhall be able to <hi>ſeperate from his love of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39.</note> but in theſe he ſhall be <hi>more then a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror;</hi> they who conſider it is written of Gods Servants, for <hi>thy ſake we are killed all the day long, and accounted ſheep for the ſlaughter,</hi> will not think much to lay down or loſe his life in the Gate, by preſſing in the narrow way to life; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince we our ſelves that Chriſt will have our <hi>all,</hi> or <hi>none of us,</hi> he will be imbraced above all, he hath declared whoſoever loveth <hi>Lands, Houſes, or Wife, or Children, or life it ſelf better then him, is not worthy of him,</hi> we then ſhall eaſily deny our ſelves, and take up our croſs and follow him; Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber we, that through much tribulation we enter into Heaven, that the true Religion and courſe of Godlineſs did and doth call for the loſs of all outward comforts, and propound future glory, a <hi>better and more during ſubſtance;</hi> we ſhall then take joyfully the ſpoyling of our goods; expectation maketh hard things to be born with eaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grave upon the ſoul principles of true Religion,</hi> the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>4</label> of the Oracles of God; for theſe as the baſis, or ground plot of any building, as the axioms of any Art or Science, or as the firſt draught of the Picture, do facilitate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the future ſtructure, and perfection; and are in all ſtraits eminently ſerviceable; Gods method to make his people walk
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46624:20"/> in his way, is to <hi>write his Law up in their hearts;</hi> uncatechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſouls having confuſed notions of faith, which through want of order, and ability, do perplex and entangle themſelves in the ways of piety, many times in a blind zeal they confound the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of Gods Ordinances; and make a defect in the one, equally heinous as in the other; and not knowing how to guide their judgments, they charge upon themſelves duties whereof their relation or condition doth deny them to be capable; be ſure you lay in the ſoul the firſt principles of the Oracles of God, and then leave them by a regular progreſs in Chriſtianity; ſure I am, that ſome, yea many ſouls are ſhip-wract for want of ballanced judgements: many loſe all by lifting themſelves up to the dignities of Saints, not once acquainting themſelves with the duties of Saints; and pretend unto the joys of beleiving, without once pondering the principles of faith; the unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, will eaſily ere from the faith; ſeducers need no better a Subject for their deſign, then ſimple ſouls affected to, but ignorant of the truth, and way to life.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>Get, keep, and exerciſe a ſpirit of diſcerning;</hi> In all your getting, get underſtanding; Wiſdom to guide our affairs will make our burden eaſie, the ſpirit of grace and ſanctification is a <hi>ſpirit of</hi> diſcerning, the ſpiritual man <hi>judgeth all things;</hi> Heavens way is in nothing ſo ſtrait and narrow as in the bounds w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich reſtrain us; the dangers which on all ſides limit it; true piety lyeth in ſuch narrow points that without a clear judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and good underſtanding we cannot hit it; the Devil and his inſtruments are ſo politique and ſubtle, that without a ſpirit of diſcerning they will readily delude, they lead cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſilly ſouls; through want of wiſedom we entangle our ſelves, and many times make ſtumbling ſtones in our own way; want of judgment cauſeth ſuperſtitious ſcrupuloſity, raſh cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, vain preſumption, and feigned reverence, he that is not able to <hi>diſcern</hi> between good and evil; will many times <hi>condemn good as evil,</hi> and take evil for good; will through fear of ſin fly duty, or be bold to ruſh into ſin without fear; he will not reſpect, or he will renounce Gods Ordinances, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of mens diſorders; or elſe he will impoſe his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:46624:20"/> and think to pleaſe God by a voluntary humility. By the ſpirit of diſcerning, beleivers muſt prove Doctrines, trie the ſpirits, diſtinguiſh Miniſters, know the Devil when appearing an Angel of light; differ Chriſts Church, from the flocks of Chriſts Companions, and diſcern Gods Ordinances from humane inventions, converſant about them, or in their room and ſtead, and direct their own converſation in, and according to the ſpeciality of duty, which the providence of God and their preſent ſtate doth require. And know how to chuſe or refuſe things indifferent, and ſever them from things neceſſary, and walk with even, upright feet according to the truth of the Goſpel. Follow God with the eaſe and freedom of thoſe Travellers who ſee and know their way; no difficulty like darkneſs in the things which are to be beleived and done, becauſe <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>eternal life</hi> is dependant thereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Give up your ſelves, your whole ſelves to the will of God.</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>6</label> is an eſtate of eaſe; nothing but a ſtubborn nature and perverſe Will can perplex them who are at the command of others: How eaſie are the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d things of Warfare, by the keeping of the Souldiers in ſtrict obedience to their Officers? ſhall not it be much more ſuch to us, if we will yeild free and full obedience to the Captain of our Salvation? Let therefore your <hi>judgement</hi> guide <hi>affection; piety,</hi> prevail againſt <hi>policy;</hi> what you <hi>ſhould,</hi> againſt what you <hi>would do.</hi> Let Gods Will once revealed become unto you the reaſon of all obedience in action, and acquieſcency in paſſion; pray heartily and in truth <hi>Father in Heaven let thy will be done,</hi> captivate carnal reaſon, and bring every proud thought and high imagination in ſubjection to the will of Chriſt, debates of fleſh and blood are diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the mind, and deſtructive to the ſoul. <hi>Paul</hi> found not a more ready way then not to reaſon with fleſh and blood, when God was pleaſed to reveal himſelf to him. Let the eye of reaſon read Gods will revealed, and then by faith ſilence the dictates, and lead c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptive this depraved power; reſignation unto Gods will is the formality of true obedience; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called <hi>obedience of faith,</hi> and this obedience can be the one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y eaſie property of Gods Children. Gods will is and can
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46624:21"/> be the onely warrant of his worſhip; to offer God mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, is to go a whoring from him, and to rebel againſt him; our Religion muſt be according to his expreſs direction. It is the great anxiety of the godly to know the will of God; but obedience or a readineſs and reſolvedneſs to beleive what he ſhall ſpeak, to do what he ſhall direct, and to ſuffer meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what he ſhall diſpoſe, is a diſcharge thereof; for he that will do, ſhall know the Will of God: the bending carnal, wrangling reaſon to the pleaſure of the moſt high, will paſs us with much eaſe through the ſtrait Gate and narrow way which doth lead to life.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>7</label> 
               <hi>Go in good Company;</hi> it is not good for <hi>man to be alone,</hi> was Gods reaſon for creating humane ſociety; ſolitude is not more ſad then dangerous; <hi>two are better then one, if one fall the other will lift up;</hi> go therefore in company towards Heaven; it is Gods direction that we ſhould aſſemble our ſelves, and go in troops to his Sanctuary, and call upon one another to go up to <hi>Zion:</hi> Chriſtian Souls ſtand charged with one another. It was a ſaying beſeeming a curſed <hi>Cain, Am I my Brothers keeper?</hi> Goſpel Counſel is that Chriſtians <hi>conſider one another,</hi> to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke unto love and good works, that they exhort one another daily, leſt any be hardened through the deceitfulneſs of ſin,</hi> and that if any be overtaken with a fault, he be <hi>reſtored by a ſpirit of meekneſs.</hi> I confeſs there are few who walk in Heavens way, and find out the ſtrait gate and narrow way, yet there are ſome and it will be hard indeed that we ſtand or go alone in the perplexing paths of life; ſay therefore as <hi>David, I am a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion for them who fear God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the choice of your company be ſure you look to two things; Keep in Gods <hi>true Church,</hi> and under Gods <hi>true Miniſters.</hi> Theſe are the moſt certain conducts unto glory, the very Ship and Pilots which convey us unto Life; by, and unto theſe are diſpenſed the promiſes of Grace, and Covenant of Salvation; union with, and ſubjection unto theſe, is our ſecurity in all ſtraits, and propriety in all the promiſes, God hath promiſed nothing to individual perſons, but all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings to and for his Church, and ſo to the Sons of <hi>Zion,</hi> as members of his Church, non-continuance in Communion
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46624:21"/> with the Church, is in Goſpel language, <hi>not holding the head,</hi> by which the whole is increaſed. Separation from the Church is moſt certainly deſtructive; to be caſt out of Chriſts Church is the ſevereſt doom on this ſide of the laſt Judgement; and to caſt our ſelves out of the Church, is the greateſt and ſadeſt ſin that can be, on this ſide the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt: They are equally in danger who throw themſelves, and who are thrown overboard by others. I could never yet know how to differ the eſtate (more then by the ſin of it) <hi>of a ſelf-excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate,</hi> and <hi>an excommunicate by the Church:</hi> Gods ordinary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and preſence of grace is confined to his Church Catholique Viſible (for of the inviſible theſe things cannot be predicated) and therefore <hi>ex Eccleſia nulla ſalus:</hi> All men of all opinions concerning the form of the Church, do agree in this, <hi>That there is no ordinary way of ſalvation out of the Church;</hi> and all Churches conſtituted of old, or gathered of late oppoſe them elves, and are oppoſed to the world; calling the men of the world into communion with them, as ever they look to be ſaved; and caſt into the World, and ſo unto Satan, the god of the world, whomſoever they cut off from the Church.</p>
            <p>The Church of God may backſlide, and be defiled; the Miniſters of God may be careleſs and negligent; yea prophane, proud and perſecuting; the ſheep may be not onely not looked after, but driven and violently ſcattered on Gods mountains; their waters may be pudled, and their paſtures trodden down; Gods Worſhip may be defiled by corrupt Appendants, and ſo his Ordinances may be diſorderly adminiſtred, and his Word may be made of none effect by mens traditions; the keys of the Kingdom may be turned againſt thoſe who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt: and theſe evils are not onely provoking unto Gods jealouſie, but alſo a ſad Omen of his departure; and the Churches approaching devaſtation and diſſolution: But yet, whilſt they continue <hi>really a Church,</hi> and <hi>relatively his Church,</hi> and retain his <hi>ſubſtantial, eſſential Worſhip</hi> and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and he continueth his own <hi>Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and preſence,</hi> though his provoked, reproving preſence; departing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulating preſence, thoſe that fear his name, and mourn for the abominations they cannot mend, muſt not withdraw themſelves, deſpiſe or neglect his Ordinances, or decline his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46624:22"/> publike, ſolemn Worſhip. When the ſons of <hi>Ely</hi> by their prophaneſs, and the violent diſorder of their Miniſtration, cauſed the people to <hi>loath the offerings of the Lord,</hi> I find not that any did leave off or forbear to bring them: And when the Image of Jealouſie was in the Temple, and brought God to the threſhold ready to depart, I find not that the people fled from it. Chriſtians, we muſt follow, not go before God: When he removeth the Candleſtick, then we may ſeek light elſewhere; but if his Ordinances <hi>abide his,</hi> though by dim and dark lights; they are in <hi>Moſes</hi> chair, and we muſt hear them. I could never yet underſtand by that caution <hi>(Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the leaven of the Phariſees) hear them not; for they teach for doctrines the traditions of men.</hi> I cannot but commend to your ferious conſideration the prayer of the men who did fear God, and Gods anſwer unto them, in a caſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order in, and defection from the true Church; it is in <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7, 8. <hi>Tell me, O thou whom my ſoul loveth, where thou feedeſt thy flock, where thou makeſt them to reſt at noon; for why ſhould I turn aſide by the flocks of thy Companions? If thou know n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, O thou faireſt among women, go thy way forth by the footſteps of the flocks, and feed thy kids beſide the ſhepheards tents:</hi> The men who feared the Lord were at a loſs for to finde and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the Aſſembly in which Gods gracious preſence might be enjoyed: they were affraid of falling into the flock of <hi>Chriſts Companions,</hi> who were <hi>ſeparated Aſſemblies,</hi> gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſelf-conſtituted Aſſemblies; worſhipping the true God with his own Ordinances, as to the matter, but by a <hi>ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Miniſtry</hi> in ſelf determined places (and ſo defective in the eſſential form) and for their profeſſion, and pretence of relation to Chriſt called his <hi>Companions:</hi> In this ſtrait they ſeriouſly enquire and pray God for direction what to do, and which way to turn; and he directeth them by two marks, as ſtanding and infallible ſigns, by which to ſteer their courſe; <hi>The footſteps of his flocks,</hi> the ſolemn celebration of his own Worſhip: And the <hi>Shepherds tents,</hi> the regular exiſtency of his Miniſters, by the order of his appointment. Give me leave to note unto you ſome obſervations of an Author, whoſe name hath more acceptance and authority with many among you then what I can ſay. He referreth this Scripture hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46624:22"/> to the ſtate of thoſe who feared God under <hi>Jerobohams</hi> ſchiſm and rebellion, and when <hi>Judah</hi> was defiled with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> High-places and Idolatry; and inferreth, <hi>A Church is black, its deformities ſtand in the fall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cotton.</note> 
               <hi>and ſins of the people and Princes; in their folly, declining to Idolatry, in their ſchiſms and rents from their mother; in their prophaneſs, apoſtacy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in Church and Commonwealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He obſerveth, <hi>there may be a true comely Church in the midſt of theſe deformities; the ſins of the Princes and people may make the Church black, but cannot take away her comelineſs; run we not therefore from the Church becauſe of her blackneſs, but run to her and embrace her in the midſt of her defections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This teacheth the children of the Church not to ſeparate from the Church for corruption ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was a ſin in them who were angry with the Church, as ſome of the ſeparation are and do depart from us: What, and if ſome caſt off</hi> England <hi>ſhall we reject her, becauſe ſome of the ſons of her Mother do ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here is ſhewed two marks of the true Church of God;</hi> The footſteps of his flocks, <hi>Aſſemblies of Gods people to his true Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; and</hi> his own Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Thus far, and in theſe words doth this reverend Author, though afterwards a great countenancer of the thing he here condemned. This I ſay Chriſtians, it may ſound harſh in your ears, but you muſt let it ſink into your hearts. The Church defiled and diſordered, muſt not be deſpiſed or declined; the Worſhip and Ordinances of God uncomfortably, unprofitably adminiſtred; yea with ſome ſuperfluous Appendants muſt not be diſowned, or determined evil; but embraced and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as his Worſhip. The criſis of pietie in this caſe, is to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our converſe with God in his own Ordinances, diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a mode, grievous yea loathſom to our ſouls; conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue our communion when we mourn for what we cannot mend. Obſerve it, Chriſts Miniſtrie was moſt vehemently, convincingly, enragingly invective againſt the erronious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, prophane and ſuperſticious lives of the Church of the Jews, and her Prieſts, and Teachers, yet he continued communion with her, and appeared an Advocate for her againſt the <hi>flocks of his companions,</hi> ſelf-gathered, conſtituted Churches;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46624:23"/> we <hi>know what we worſhip; Salvation is of the Jews:</hi> So long as Gods Ordinances are ſalvably diſpenſed, take heed to your own perſonal actions, in any impoſed or directed evils, and diſorders; mourn over the impoſition and adminiſtration which may extend a guilt on the Church collectively, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own not the Church, deſpiſe not the Miniſtry, decline not the Worſhip whilſt they exiſt the <hi>Lords.</hi> Look to it that your zeal to purity, break not unity; and your loathing humane inventions, make you not leave Gods Inſtitutions: You are Chriſts ſheep, as you will be led, be looked after by the ſhepherd and Biſhop of your ſouls, ſee to it that you leap not out of his fold. You may have your waters pudled, your paſtures trodden, the proud of the flock to puſh you with horn and with hoof; your Paſtors may rule you with pride and with crueltie, <hi>Lording it over Gods heritage;</hi> and you (they being careleſs of you) may be diſperſed: But I beſeech you, when the great ſhepherd ſhall come to judge between ſheep and ſheep, between you and your ſhepherds, let him finde you on the <hi>mountains of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.</note> though ſcattered and afflicted. Communion with the Church under corruption may not be very comfortable, but be aſſured it ſhall be ſafe. Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be mournfully endeavoured, but Separation will never effect it, it will for ever hinder, ſupplant, ſubvert it. I muſt tell you my determination is by Gods grace to <hi>ſeek pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Ordinances in union with the Church,</hi> and by non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming communion to witneſs againſt, and endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move diſorder and corruption.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Go continually Armed;</hi> your courſe of piety is a conſtant <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>8</label> militation, be then wary Souldiers, be Armed Cap-a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe, take unto you the whole Armour of <hi>God, that you may be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the evil day;</hi> have your Loyns girt with <hi>verity,</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of truth, the ſpirit of a ſound mind; your breaſt guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the <hi>breſtplate of Righteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12.</note> integrity of heart; your head covered with the <hi>helmet of hope,</hi> which will under the greateſt Billows and moſt roaring Waves hold your head above the water; have your feet ſhod with patience, the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations of the Goſpel of peace.</hi> In every ſtep you ſet you have ſharp ſhells, heart-peircing, paſſion-provoking croſſes, loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:46624:23"/> diſtreſſes and afflictions, you <hi>have need of patience, that when you have done the Will of God you may inherit the promiſe;</hi> you cannot without patience continue in well doing unto the obtainment of the Glory, <hi>honour, immortality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.27.</note> 
               <hi>and eternal life,</hi> which you do ſeek; take with you the <hi>ſhield of faith</hi> in Gods declared will for Doctrine or practiſe, in Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious properties, and gracious promiſes, thoſe will quench the moſt fiery darts of the Devil; take unto you <hi>the Sword of the Spirit,</hi> the Word of God, to cut down your way, kill your Luſt, the Worlds allurements, and the Devils ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; thus armed ſtand faſt in your Chriſtian reſolution, but move forward; advance in your Chriſtian converſation, and you ſhall with eaſe encounter and overcome all oppoſition for the Captain of our Salvation hath led our enemies captive, and looketh that we defend our own ſouls againſt the ſubtile, malicious ſtroaks of a ſubdued, though our ſworn Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gueſs your way by the compaſs of the Covenant,</hi> the Lord <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>9</label> hath condeſcended to deal with man by way of Covenant, for the effecting of his Salvation; this is a Covenant of Grace, <hi>Grace</hi> is the <hi>ground of it,</hi> it was freely made, for we had no obligation on Gods Juſtice, or power to conſtrain or exact it; <hi>Grace is the matter of it,</hi> I will be your God, you ſhall be my people, you ſhall walk in my ways, my ſpirit ſhall be in your hearts; <hi>Grace is the form of it,</hi> I will be your God, I will write my Law on your hearts, I will put my ſpirit within you, you ſhall walk in my ways, my grace ſhall be ſufficient for you; <hi>Grace is the end of it,</hi> our ſanctification here, and our ſalvation hereafter, and the means neceſſary unto both in the way of their obtainment; and our purſuit of them; This Covenant is the Contract of the Bible, the compendium of the Goſpel, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is Mediator, the <hi>Miniſters</hi> are diſpencers, <hi>Ordinances</hi> are the diſpenſations, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> are the conditions, <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> with all good things is the matter of this everlaſting Covenant; this Covenant, like a Compaſs, points at all parts of Heaven; when we are in the wide Ocean of the World, out of ſight of any Land to guide us, we may ſtear by this Compaſs to our deſired Haven; when we are in darkneſs and danger between the narrow Creeks, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:46624:24"/> ſtrait paſſages of <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Caribdis,</hi> this <hi>Covenant</hi> is a light, a Lanthorn at Land to guide us, unto that Nick and narrow point which will ſecure us?</p>
            <p>Chriſtians, the comfort of this Covenat is not known till being ſhut up from men, ſecluded from Ordinances, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the want of all means (it may be ſo much as a Bible) you begin to reflect your Relation to God, Gods Diſpenſations of grace to man, and call to mind the Indenture, and Charter which doth ſecure, declare, and direct both; This Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant will diſſolve our doubts, direct our duties, and dictate our comforts in all ſtraits, in all conditions, this and that I muſt do, or not do; this and that I muſt expect, or not expect; this is or that is truth, or Error will be eaſily infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by him, who is intereſted in, and underſtandeth the Covenant of Salvation; by this, when I a poor Gentile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>Abraham</hi> is <hi>ignorant of me,</hi> and <hi>Jacob knoweth me not,</hi> can yet cry unto the Lord <hi>thou art my God;</hi> by this when I am in the Furnace; I can cry unto the Lord, my God, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him, anſwering me my people; I can underſtand by this the word which ſpeaketh unto us as Children, ſay, <hi>my Son deſpiſe not the chaſtening of the Lord;</hi> I hereby know cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, paternal caſtigation to be the reſult of affection from God, and relation to God, and ſo when <hi>I ſit in darkneſs and can ſee no light, I can truſt in the name of the Lord,</hi> and ſtay my ſelf upon my God, faithful in Covenant, who will not fail me; I hereby diſcern ſin, and detect errour to be eſchewed; diſcover truth and duty to be embraced and purſued. In a Word, what the word doth more amply and abundantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare when I am at liberty to uſe, the Covenant of Grace doth ſuggeſt, and from thence I may infer it for my comfort and guidance when reſtrained; the good therein promiſed I may boldly challenge; the evil thereunto repugnant I muſt rejct; the truth and dutie thereby dictated I muſt receive, and do; you look for experience, and I tell you this in the uprightneſs of my heart, in my late condition the Covenant of Grace was my great comfort, the conſideration of the Covenant was my councel. I would not for all the world have been ignorant of, unintereſted in, or eſtranged unto the Covenant of God: <hi>Go you and do likewiſe.</hi> If you are confounded in your paſſage to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46624:24"/> life, it is for want of the Compaſs of the Covenant, or skill to uſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Go forward in Heavens way,</hi> being entred the ſtrait <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Help </seg>10</label> gate and narrow way ſtand not ſtill; motion will make it eaſie: Travellers are more tired at the beginning then end of their journey, becauſe not uſed to ſuch vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence; cuſtom in all things become a ſecond nature; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you do go not back; <hi>non progredi eſt regredi</hi> in heavens way; not to go forward is to go backward: The enemy will come upon you, if you advance not againſt him: <hi>Remember Lots wife;</hi> take heed of backſliding, you will thereby hinder your ſelves in heavens way, and wound your conſciences; take heed of <hi>Apoſtacy from the faith,</hi> you will thereby ruine your ſalvation and hurt religion. Conſider, <hi>The juſt live</hi> (that is perſevere in grace and holineſs) <hi>by faith;</hi> but if any man draw back Gods ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him. Be it your care not to be found in the number of them <hi>who draw back unto perdition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>but of them who beleeve unto ſalvation of their ſoul:</hi> Having begun in the Spirit do not end in the fleſh; inure your ſelves unto hardſhip, be <hi>ſtedfaſt and unmovable,</hi> and you cannot but <hi>abound in the work of the Lord,</hi> nor ſhall your <hi>labour be in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved Friends, the way to life being bounded with ſuch dangerous precipices, beſet with ſuch difficulties and oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and your depraved nature being apt to wander, averſe and indiſpoſed to diligence and activity in holineſs, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but find <hi>ſtrait is the gate, and narrow is the way which leadeth unto life, and few there be who finde it.</hi> But I beſeech you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, chuſe to enter, it is <hi>the way to life: Strive to enter, it is ſtrait;</hi> obſerve, practice theſe Directions now given, by Gods grace your entrance will be an act of eaſe and ſucceſs. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what you have heard, and the Lord give you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
